<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divinity and philosophy dissected, and set forth, by a mad man. The first booke, divided into three chapters. Chap. I. The description of the world in mans heart: with the articles of the Christian Faith. Chap. II. A description of one spirit acting in all, which some affirme is God. Chap. III. A description of the Scripture according to the history and mystery thereof.</title>
            <author>Mad man.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E53_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E53[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divinity and philosophy dissected, and set forth, by a mad man. The first booke, divided into three chapters. Chap. I. The description of the world in mans heart: with the articles of the Christian Faith. Chap. II. A description of one spirit acting in all, which some affirme is God. Chap. III. A description of the Scripture according to the history and mystery thereof.</title>
                  <author>Mad man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [3].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philosophy and religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIVINITY AND PHILOSOPHY Diſſected, and ſet forth, by a mad Man.</p>
            <p>The firſt Booke, divided into three Chapters.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. I. <hi>The deſcription of the World in mans heart: with the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>A deſcription of one ſpirit acting in all, which ſome affirme is God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>A deſcription of the Scripture according to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory and myſtery thereof.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> Printed in the Yeare, 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111751:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111751:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Friend and Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is Divinity and Philoſophy diſſected and laid open to the view of the world, by a mad man; therefore if the manner &amp; phraſe be not ſo exact, as that it is not able to ſatisfie the curious eye, or abide the cenſure of the nice Mercurialliſt (who is apt to carpe more at the miſplacing or neglect of words then matter) it is no great wonder, nor care I whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be ſatisfied or not, ſeeing my intention is to declare the matter according to my own mad minde, unto thoſe who will under ſtand it after my mad manner: The reaſons why I expoſe it to the generall view needs not much be queſtioned or inquired after in this age, wherein the whole world is full of ſo many diſtracted heads and religions (which ſay, Loe here, and loe there is Chriſt) that many are put beſides their wits in ſtraining them out of joynt to inquire with Pilate what is truth; by which it may be gathered that in many ages the ſame hath been in obſcurity without being diſcovered or ſearcht after: nor are there any to bee found amongst the multitudes of thoſe who beare the name of men, that are able, or at leaſt willing to rectifie them by reſolving the queſtion. Wherefore I have thruſt my ſelfe upon the Theatre in this mad poſture and act, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing my mad minde amongſt the reſt, to prove if any will accept my madneſſe for truth, the which I dare not avouch for truth to all, becauſe I know moſt men are full of ſelf conceited or imaginary knowledge; ſo that if the higheſt, divineſt and greateſt wiſdome and truth that can be written or expreſſed by letters, were laid down to them, they will not admit of, nor receive it in their underſtandings, but will eſteeme of it as the greateſt blaſphemy, folly and lie in the world. Beſides, I am not ſo ignorant in my madneſſe, but that I know likewiſe that ſeverall eyes and judgements will looke upon and into it, and according to their eye or judgement, it will appeare to or in them, and ſo I doe expect their thoughts and verdicts to paſſe upon it: therefore I ſay, I will not, nor dare not maintaine it to them, in reſpect of their various capacities, concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſpoſitions, but only leave it to the diverſitie of cenſures as every one doth finde it to or in them, earneſtly deſiring that they may underſtand the beſt ſenſe for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or profit, which is my reall intention. As alſo I propound it for a triall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there be any in this uncharitable and ſelfe loving age, that out of true love and
<pb facs="tcp:111751:3"/>ſound judgement will extend his hand to helpe a mad man, and anſwer him ſo as is able throughly to rectifie and cure his judgement in demonſtrating to him by more probable, ſubſtantiall and apparant reaſons, his error in this following Treatiſe, &amp; be his director to a more ſublime and higher truth in the thing treated of. I doubt not but the truly divine, and right reaſonable, or the truly wiſe, able and ſound in judgement, is ſo wiſe and good, that he is able and willing to cure diſtempers of all ſorts, to whom I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes willing to ſubmit my judgement upon better grounds: however, deare Reader, whoſoever thou art, whether friend or enemy, whether wiſe or mad man, I wiſh thee no leſſe happineſſe then to my ſelfe, who deſire to be in my wits and right minde to God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a fool and mad man to the world: if thoſe things ſpoken here, trouble or offend thee, ſo as thou conceive hatred or malice againſt me for the ſame, or that thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt that any prejudice may redound to thy owne or others judgements (or religions) by this enſuing Diſcourſe, I beſeech thee pacifie thy ſelfe firſt, and judge not raſhly, or before thou knoweſt, nor blame me, but firſt enter in judgement with thy ſelfe, by pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and conſidering in thy ſelfe, that if thou hadſt ever under ſtood or known things aright thou couldſt never have been offended at any thing ſpoken, or at leaſt intended for thy good, much leſſe could the words of a mad man have ſtumbled or offended thee, for to the wiſe all things are profitable: but if any doe reap good thereby, let them know that out of a hearty love I earneſtly intend good to them and to all, and wiſh from my heart that they may attaine unto the perfection thereof, for their owne everlaſting peace and tranquility in minde: nor is it impoſſible but perhaps that which ſeemeth to be a lie and madneſſe to ſome, may appeare to be the reall truth and true wiſdome to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; thus wiſhing thee the true knowledge of all things and their cauſe, together with the fruition and enjoyment of the trueſt happineſſe, which is God: I am thy true friend.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 21. line 36. For negative read vegitative. p. 22. l. 16. r. feeleth. p. 37. l. 21. r. taſte of.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111751:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The deſcription of the world in Mans heart.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for the creation of the world, it is in Mans heart, as Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes ſaith in the third Chapter, it is internally; and in the firſt of the Hebrewes, he ſaith that God hath created the worlds, ſpeaking in the plurall number; that is, he makes a firſt and ſecond creation of Man: now the creation of Gods firſt world in Man, is Man and God joyned together from eternity; and this was that deep ſilence and waters that God moved or brooded on, and he ſeparated the waters from the waters, for God is that light and holy ſpring, and Man is that darke and blacke water; and God is the Heaven, and Man is the Earth; and the ſeparation is the firſt day for diſtinctions ſake that we may know God from our ſelves, I meane the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament and ſeparating light and darkneſſe is the diſtinction; and that is the firſt day in Man which is called the Evening and the Morning: So theſe waters is the flowing of the mindes of God and Man which was ſeparated; the minde of God floweth above the firmament and in his owne light or ſphere or in himſelfe. The Man, his minde floweth under the firmament and on the earth or in himſelfe, that his dry land or earth might appeare; and this ſeparation of mindes or waters is the ſecond day or light that diſcovers two, one diſcourſing to the other, and ſaith, let us make or doe theſe things, and ſo this day or light hath its evening and morning, which is a whole day: and God ſaith, let the Earth bring forth fruits; now the deſires and affections are the herbs and fruits with their ſeeds, that is their proper ſelves that bringeth forth their owne kinde in Man, for every affection, thought and inclination, hath its owne ſeed in it ſelfe, and doth produce its own fruit out of us, which is good in their owne kinde; and the appearance of theſe things in us is the third day in man, with its evening and morning, for the evening and morning maketh the whole day. And God ſaid, let there be light in the firmament, which light is the Son and glory of God and Man Chriſt Jeſus, and is the light which diſtinguiſhes or diſcovers the mindes both of God and Man to each other: and the Moon that is in this diſtinction that rules the night or the darke Man, is the inſtruction, and the good adviſes, that the Sunne or true day light ſhineth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111751:4"/>through them to the Man, and all the ſtarres in this firmament are the lights of Gods graces that is ſeverall to the Man to enlighten his darke heart that hee might ſee the glorious Son through theſe gimmering lights, for his dark eyes is not able at the firſt to behold the glorious Sonne, but by degrees the holy God brings him to it; ſo theſe holy lights in the Man are the fourth day with his evening and morning. And God ſaid, let the waters bring forth fowle and fiſhes; which waters are the flowing ſea of thy minde, and the fowle or birds are the flying fantaſies that flye about the heaven of our ſouls, and the fiſhes are thy delightfull thoughts that ſwim up and downe in thy minde, and all theſe are proper ſelves with their ſeeds, and are very good in their owne kinde, and are uſefull for the Man, and for his pleaſure and delight; and this is the fifth day in man with its evening and morning. And God ſaid, let the Earth bring forth all beaſts and creeping things; which beaſts is the paſſions of thy minde, ſome of which thou maieſt uſe and eat of, and ſome thou muſt keep under and not eat of, as the Hare which is thy fearfull paſſions, and the Swine which is thy voluptuous appetite, and the birds and fiſhes (which will not be orderly) thou muſt keep under and not taſte of; for we muſt reigne and keep our phantaſies (that is the ravenous and deſtructive birds) hood winkt, that they may not ſee nor goe beyond their limits to diſturbe the ſoule with their diſorderlineſſe; for <hi>David</hi> did kill a Lion and a Bear, and fought with <hi>Goliah</hi> and killed him; which Lion is thy ſtrong unruly appetite, and the Beare is thy unorderly and bloody ſelfe will, and the <hi>Goliah</hi> is that evill or divell, that is thy unreaſonableneſſe that raileth againſt thy God, or good which is thy reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe. Now theſe thoughts and phantaſies (unruly paſſions, appetites and unreaſonableneſſe) muſt be kept under and ruled, or elſe they will diſturbe and deſtroy thy ſoul, but kept under, ruled and ordered are uſefull to the Man; but this keeping them under is death to them, for they are mad and cruell (let looſe) and keeps the ſoule and reaſon in all ſubjection, ſo that no good ſhall appeare in the ſoule but they will deſtroy it; for theſe beaſts, birds and fiſhes, will deſtroy and devoure all the reſt of the peaceable beaſts, birds and fiſhes (as the dove, or thy innocencie or meek lambe, or peaceableneſſe) and all thoſe peaceable creatures that would be at reſt in thee, and pleaſe thee, and give thee reſt: for <hi>Sampſon</hi> killed that Lion that came roaring upon him, that was his ſtrong and ravening appetite that would have devoured him, ſo he ſaith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward (when he had overcome his ravening appetite) there came ſweetnes out thereof where with he was refreſhed; for he ſaith, out of the eater came meat, and out of the ſtrong came ſweetneſſe, ſo that appetite that would have devoured him (keepſt under and ſet upon the love or deſire of goodneſſe) was meat and ſweetneſſe to him. And God and Man ſaid, let us make or ſet forth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111751:4"/>our image, which is male and female, that is true righteouſneſſe, holineſſe and pureneſſe, that ſhould rule over theſe birds, beaſts, fiſhes, and all creeping things that moveth in the world of Man; and they give them names accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their natures and qualities that they ſee in them: ſo this is the ſixth day in Man with its evening and morning, and all things is good in their kinde. So the reſt of Gods diſcovering (or creating things) is that holy reſt and dwelling of God and good in the Man, for he hath ſhewed Man all things, and he diſcovers himſelfe the laſt, which is the beſt and holy reſt and peace of things, and is the Sabbath or ſeventh day with its evening and morning, the holy reſt in man which hee ſhould have kept for ever, and never have loſt or broken: this reſt is the holy Godhead or breath of life that is given to the Man, and is light of his light, and the life of his life, or breath of his breath; for Man without God is dead, and his life and breath is death without the life and breath of God: So God gave himſelfe into the hands of Man to ſee what he would doe with him, for he loveth the Man as himſelfe. Now when the Man ſeeth that God hath given all things in his owne power, then comes the ſubtileſt beaſt that is in the earth of Man to intice or allure the Man, and to be maſter of all in him, and to rule all things, and this beaſt is the wiſdome of the fleſh, or the wiſdome of the darke man which is ſenſuall and devilliſh; and now the Man or female having her will, and beeing free, having all things in her poſſeſſion by the free gift &amp; love of God to her, deſires to rule by her will and wiſdome, and to let God alone, and forſake his counſell and wiſdom, &amp; rule by herſelf and wiſdome, which is blind, ſenſuall and evill, and this is her guide, and ſhe will be her own God to do her will, luſts and deſires, and ſhe in blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wil diſtinguiſh between good and evill, who knowes nothing at all but by the light of Gods grace and goodneſſe in her, which ſhe hath forſaken, and is ruled by her owne ſelfe and wiſdome, that calls good evill, and evill good, and ſo it is all lies and falſhood which the Man is ruled by; and ſo he is loſt and damned from God and goodneſſe, and is joyned to a lie and deceitfulneſſe, and hath made God taſte of her deceitfulneſſe by her forſaking him: for ſhee that is his wife hath forſaken him which is her mate and yoak fellow, and ſo he is loſt and hidden from her, and is under her earthly man of ſin, which is in hell: for that which ſhould be uppermoſt is undermoſt (which is God) and that which ſhould bee undermoſt is uppermoſt, for all thy brutiall paſſions and beaſtly appetites (which ſhould bee keept undermoſt and ruled) is upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and they rule and governe thee, and all things in thee, for they keep God and goodneſſe under them and will not let them appeare in thee, but kills and crucifies them as ſoone as they appeare in thee to give thee counſell for thy good; and ſo the Lambe of God is ſlaine in the beginning of our firſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111751:5"/>world, or at the firſt appearance, diſcovering and diſtinctions of things in us; for in one infancie or nonage, all things is in ſilence, and we are a Chaos, and God is in this ſilence, and with us in this Chaos, and in his time and when hee ſaw the ripeneſſe of this Chaos, he ſet forth all things in us, and made them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their order and places to us, and gave all things to us as our owne, and in our owne power, becauſe we ſhould be free to binde our ſelves or ſtand free according to our pleaſure; for there was life and death ſet before us, ſo that we might binde our ſelves to either or ſtand free as we were, and binde our ſelves to neither, becauſe that Man ſhould not complaine, nor grieve in his ſpirit that he ſhould be tyed againſt his will to any thing, therefore all men appear free to ſtand or fall, or binde themſelves to what they pleaſe: but Man tyes himſelfe to the brutiall paſſions of his mind, and leaves God and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo they be hidden and loſt in him, ſo thy paſſions, rules &amp; domineers over thee, and thy blinde wiſdome or ſubtle ſerpent carries thee into all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiefe and lies, and deceives thee, and makes thee have a helliſh mind which is a cage of all unclean and hatefull birds: for thou art the kingdome of hell, and thou art full of hell-hounds, dogs and ſwine, wolfes, and Tygers, Lions, and Beares, Serpents, and Cockatrices, and all venomous things, ſo that there is no good thing in thee in thy off-fallen eſtate, for if God or goodneſſe ſhould appeare in thee, thy beaſtly and diviliſh crew would deſtroy him out of thee, ſo that thy God or goodneſſe doth lye under thy earth (or under thy helliſh bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) which a mighty power holding forth a ſlickering ſword, which is the law of ſin that cries vengeance, and ſaith, I will repay, and ſaith, thou muſt dye, and all thy helliſh crew: for this law requires death for death, eye for eye, and tooth for tooth, for thou haſt killed God and goodneſſe, and theſe murthers flyeth in thy face by this mighty power with the ſword of juſtice in his hand, that ſtands to execute thee and kill thee for killing: and this is the patience of the Saints, which ſaith that they that killeth by the ſword muſt dye by the ſword; for this is juſtice that the blood-thirſty might drinke blood, and ſo Man thou ſhalt never bee happy till this juſtice is executed upon thee and upon all thy helliſh crew, and that thou art dead, buried, damned and loſt with Chriſt and God, and that thou and thy wicked crew is ſeen no more, and thou art turned to thy duſt, and into thy old ſilence with God againe, and art as if thou wert not; and then God in his time will create thee a new world, and renue all things againe in thee; for there ſhall bee new heavens and a new earth, wherein ſhall dwell righteouſneſſe in thee. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Create in me a new heart, O Lord, and renue a right ſpirit within mee; that is, when thy old world, or Adam is deſtroyed in thee, that Man of ſinne, or that veſſell of wrath that was borne for deſtruction or to be damned; for our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111751:5"/>old world is to ſhew the glory and juſtice of God and his mighty power in the Man, and to the Man, and that the Man ſhould ſee himſelfe loſt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and when he is come to this paſſe then ſhall he ſee his mighty power in ſaving him, and creating him a new creature or new world: for the firſt world was to ſhew the manhood, and all her glory, what ſhe is, and that all things were given into her hands to doe what ſeemed good in her own eyes: and ſhe let all things run diſorderly and ſpoyled all things, and that which ſhe ſhould have governed did governe her, ſo that all things is turned upſide down, and Man ſees his owne ſtrength and wiſdome is fooliſhneſſe: for God lets man alone with his firſt creation, to ſhew him what he is in his own free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and if man had not been left alone and free, and had not had all things in his owne power, he would have repined, therefore he was left free to ſee his owne weakneſſe and inability: ſo he deſired to be his owne God and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, therefore God gave man all things in his power, yea even himſelfe alſo, to ſee how he would uſe him, for God ſaw mans covetous deſires, and ſo God put himſelfe and all things elſe into his hands to do what ſeemed good in his own eyes, and ſo nature or man appeared, for that that is naturall is firſt, and is the firſt Adam, and that which is ſpirituall is laſt, and laſt Adam or God; for the firſt man Adam is earthly, and the laſt Man or Adam, is the heavenly or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head Man: ſo man if he deſres not to be changed, or become the laſt Adam, ſhall remain for ever in his firſt eſtate, creation or firſt world, for his firſt world is his miſery, becauſe he deſires to be his owne guide, and his blinde wiſdome is his owne deſtruction; and becauſe he diſregards all good, ſo hee ſhall bee with himſelfe and his helliſh crew till he is weary of himſelfe, for he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven himſelfe to pride, which makes him thinke he is better then other men, which is a lie and a deceit: and he is given to covetouſneſſe of the riches of this world, which all periſh with the uſing; and he is given to luxury, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and drunkenneſſe, which makes him ready to ſtarve, another time for miſpending the goods he getteth to maintaine his livelihood: and he is given to ſeek honour and worldly eſtimation, to wrath and furiouſneſſe, about theſe things which are all lies and vanities, and periſh with the uſing; and to back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting and evill ſurmiſing one another, to murder in ſecret and openly, to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred malice and hypocriſie, with all uncharitableneſſe, about theſe lies which all periſh with the uſing, for here is nothing but howling, crying, ſighing and mourning, about theſe lies and deceiveable things: for when pride hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted a man to honour and great eſtimation, then he rejoyees, and that is his heaven or God to him; and ſtraight envy in another man is troubled at this his honour and greatneſſe, and deviſes ſome plot to throw him downe, and when he is throwne downe, that is hell and death to him, then hee ſighs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111751:6"/>mourns and grieves for this deceiveable lie; and the covetous man he covets the riches of this world, and will coſen, lie and cheat any man to make himſelf rich thereby, and many times comes fire and deſtroyes his riches, or one back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter or ſlanderer or other, deviſes ſome miſchiefe againſt him, and bringeth him under the penalty of ſome law of men, that he pretendeth he hath broken, whereby all his riches that he hath gotten is loſt and taken from him, then hee mournes and grieves, becauſe this deceiveable god hath left him, and is fled, leaving him comfortleſſe; and the glutton and drunkard that lives in luxury and voluptuouſneſſe (which is his heaven or god) when penury, want and grievous diſeaſes commeth upon him, then cries he out againſt himſelfe, and grieves at his folly, which is a hell to him, now when it is too late; yet ſo ſoon as he recovers health and means againe, he returnes as bad as he was before, like the dog to his own vomit, and the ſowe that is waſhed to her wallowing in the mire: and the murtherer that in his wrath and choller doth kill a man (which murder in his paſſion is the heaven or god of lies that pleaſed him) afterwards when the law of ſin, or juſtice of man, comes to execute him, then juſtice or the law of ſin executing its office, proves a hell unto him: therefore if thou deſireſt no harme to be done to thee, thou oughteſt not to doe any to another, but if thou doſt, this revenge (or juſtice in him whom thou wrongeſt and does to him as thou wouldeſt not he ſhould do to thee) retort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> backe upon thy ſelfe, and thy owne conſcience cannot deny but that it is juſt and good, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be death and hell to thee, and that thou canſt not abide to ſuffer it, for thy juſtice and law of ſin ſaith, an eye for eye, tooth for tooth, and life for life: the morall Law and ten Commandements is in thy ſelfe, and it is thy own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall deſires to them, for thou loveſt God or good with all thy ſoule, minde and ſtrength to be done to thee, and thou doſt naturally love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, becauſe he is thy Samaritane, and doth good to thee, for thou doſt naturally love thoſe that doe thee good, and that is reaſonable; thou doſt love the Sabbath day, for naturally thou doſt love reſt, and naturally thou doſt love and honour the place from which thou cameſt which is thy father and mother; thou doſt not naturally deſire to be killed, therefore thou ſaieſt, I muſt not kill; thou doſt not deſire any ſhould take thy naturall propriety from thee, nor falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be done to thee, therefore thou ſayeſt, I muſt not wrong another man by enjoying his wife and propriety, or rob or ſteale from him his right, or what he hath laboured for, for the labourer is worthy of his hire; thou doeſt naturally hate to have a falſe accuſation on thee, therefore thou doſt ſay, I muſt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt any one, and ſo the reſt is what thou wouldeſt not have done to thee that thou muſt not doe to another; for S. Paul cryed out againſt himſelfe, and ſaid, that he did the thing he hated, and did
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111751:6"/>diſallow, and did not the thing that he did allow and love, but ſold himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law of ſin which he hated; for this law and curſe is added becauſe of the tranſgreſſion, which is juſt to reward every man according to his works, for this law of workes ſaves no man, but condemnes all becauſe all men have ſinned; and as long as man lives in the fleſhly luſts of ſin and concupiſcence, he is under this law of ſin and curſe, and cannot pleaſe God: but the world is miſtaken of Paul, and thinks that he meant and ſaid that as long as he lived in the fleſh (or in this organicall creature of the foure elements of clay) hee ſhould ſin; if this were the meaning of St. Paul, ſure he muſt kill himſelfe, and adviſe all men to doe the like, or elſe they could not pleaſe God, for that which hinders us from pleaſing of God muſt be taken out of the way; but Paul ſaith, that Chriſt hath taken him away from the curſe and law of ſin by faith, which faith is the power of perſwaſion, and convincing the heart of ſin and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and the workes of faith is to crucifie the ſinfull fleſh and luſts, and to be obedient to God and goodneſſe, and that faith of Chriſt ſaves thee: and Paul ſaith, that he thanks God he is dead, and that Chriſt is now his life, and that he lives now by the faith of the Son of God, which is by his loving per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, and that confidence and reality of truth which he found by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt in him to God and goodneſſe, and ſo that fleſh of Paul is dead and crucified to him, ſo that it is evident by the ſenſe of Scripture that Paul meant that fleſh of ſin, and not the organicall creature that he then lived in: for we know nothing of God nor of the divell, but what we ſee in our ſelves: for St. John ſaith, what we have heard and ſeen and taſted, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you; for we muſt not imagine the powerfull and mighty God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head to be any Idea, Image, or likeneſſe of any thing, but what he hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to be to us; for it is ſaid, that Chriſt is in us, and God is in Chriſt, ſo that the Godhead lives bodily in us that hath ceaſed from ſin, for of that om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent and mighty power that upholdeth and diſcovereth all things, wee know nothing neither of our ſelves or any thing elſe but what he pleaſeth to diſcover unto us: therefore in thy firſt creation, or firſt birth, God diſcovers thy ſelfe to thee which is Eſau or Adam, and thou haſt all things in thy poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thou art the God and Lord of all, for thou art the God of this firſt world that hath blinded thine owne eyes with thy ſerpent ſubtilty and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh, and thou art aſhamed of the naked truth, that is the light of Gods grace to diſcover and lay all things naked and bare before thee; but thou covereſt and hides the truth with the leaves of thy owne fruits, for thou art aſhamed of the truth, and when God calls thee in the coole of his day, and that his light and fire begins to wax cold in thee, thou hideſt thy ſelfe from him and art aſhamed of him as thy nakedneſſe, for thy wiſdome hath opened
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111751:7"/>thine eyes to thy ſelfe will, and hath ſhut them up to the naked truth, and ſo thou art loſt and damned from God and goodneſſe, for thou haſt deprived thy ſelfe of him, and hath hid God in thy ſelfe as thy ſhame, for thou art aſhamed to come before him, and therefore thou hideſt him with thy partition walls of ſinne, and now thou art cloathed with thy owne death, that is the law of ſin, and thy owne juſtice in thee; for the skinnes of thy innocency that thou haſt lulled within thee (which is the death of God and Chriſt) is thy cloathing, and ſo thou art cloathed with the death of God in thee, and God now never appeares to thee but in this death, with terror and feare which terrifies thee, and this juſtice of terror and feare lyeth in the death of God, which thou haſt ſlaine and diſ-regarded, and is that ſlickering ſword that keeps this death (which was the tree of life) till thou be killed by it as thou haſt killed: as it is ſaid, I have been dead but now am alive for evermore, for this tree of life is the Lambe of God that is ſlaine in the beginning of our firſt world, and ſo hee lyeth dead to us till our wicked world is at an end, and this our wicked world ſhall bring forth nothing but thornes and thiſtles, which is ſins that ſhall prick thee to the heart, and thou ſhalt eat of thy owne fruits with the ſweat of thy browes; that is the labour of thy ſinnes, that toyleth thee with their labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and this toyle ſhalt thou have with thy ſinnes till thou returneſt to thy duſt againe, or to thy old ſilence wherein thou wert before, and thy ſerpent (or ſleſhly wiſdome) ſhall goe creeping on thy earthly beeing of ſin, and ſhall live on their duſt or firſt originall, which is lies, and is thy ſubtle ſerpents food, and thy husband which is thy lie or unreaſonableneſſe that thou haſt united thy ſelf to) ſhall rule and domineere over thee, and thou ſhalt be ſubject to his will, and all thy children or ſinnes that he begetteth of thee thou ſhalt bring forth in ſorrow, and they ſhall be a pain unto thee; for what is ſaid to Adam is ſaid to both, for ſhe or he is one, and is the female of God, for man or woman ſignifies both, and this ſword of juſtice which ſtandeth in the death of Chriſt, is the enmity the ſeed of the woman or humaine nature, that ſhall breake the ſerpents head, and deſtroy his ſeed; and this enmity ſhall bruiſe the humanities heele or foot that he ſhall never walke any more in falſe wayes; ſo this enmity or ſword ſtandeth in the death of Chriſt, crying vengeance and ſaith, that this world (or Adam, Edom, or Eſau) is the childe of wrath, and he hath prepared or ordained himſelf to deſtruction, and ſo this whole world of Man is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, damned and utterly loſt, and Man ſhall never bee happy in his firſt birth, becauſe of his fall, for he muſt be dead, buried and borne againe, or elſe hee ſhall never enter into the Kingdome of heaven, for his owne nature is wrath, but God did not make him ſo, but his nature was ſo for ever, for according to Scripture we are the children of wrath by nature, and at the firſt wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111751:7"/>ſo, and God did make him appeare to himſelfe what he was, and gave himſelfe and all things into his power, that he might not complaine, and that the Man might ſee how he would uſe God himſelfe, and all things in him, and ſo he deſtroyes himſelfe, God, and all things within him, and hath ordained himſelfe and all to be loſt, ſo the firſt creation in Man is loſt, and God ſhewes Man his miſerable condition in this death and loſſe of God and goodneſſe, and the power of God that lyeth in this death, is called the death of Chriſt, or the two edged ſword that ſtandeth to divide the ſoule aſunder, or that fleſh of Chriſt that is the curtaine that ſtands before the moſt holy place, or <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum:</hi> and this power of Chriſt is in hell under our earthly beeing and Man of ſinne, till we and all ours is turned to duſt againe, and this power or death ſtayes with patience and long ſufferance under us in hell till we are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our ſelves and ſins, for we grieve the Spirit of God by whom we are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and he daily ſhews us our owne miſery, and toyle and ſorrow ſinne doth make in us, and this toyl we ſhall have for ever till we are weary of our ſelves and deſire to be ended with all our hearts, and to forſake our ſelves and our owne wicked world, and all that is within us that is wicked, then doth this holy power, Man himſelfe in us, and deſtroyes us and all within us, and turns us to our duſt againe; and when we are in ſilence with God againe, then doth he create us anew and make us a new world, and prepares us a bride for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, a heavenly Jeruſalem, a City and houſe for God, and he is our Lord and husband, and he is a holy and righteous ruler, and doth governe all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our ſoule in peace and love, with all orderlineſſe and union, for then the Lion (our ſtrongeſt paſſions) is in peace with the lambe or innocencie, and all our other beaſts, birds and fiſhes (which is our phantaſies) is orderly and in peace; then ſhall the childe or innocencie lay his hand on the Cockatrice hole, and the Wolves, Beares and Lions ſhall be together, and one ſhall not ſting or hurt the other, for God is King and ruler in man, which orders all things well and in peace in him, and the Son of glory or God, ſhines ſeven times more brighter then hee did in the former world, and this glorious world or Man of God ſhall laſt for ever and ever, in his glorious tranſcendent bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and there is no ſorrow or paine in this world, but everlaſting raviſhing joyes and ſweet content of minde; for this holy God doth raviſh the ſoule continually with his delectable pleaſures, ſo the ſoule is ever ſatisfied; for God when he is our Lord, and we have given our ſelves to him, hee uſes us thus ſweetly, and doth give us all pleaſure and content, but when he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to us in our firſt creation, and firſt world, we were aſhamed of him, and hid and deſtroyed him from us, but he is not aſhamed of us, but uſes us with all love; for nature appeared firſt and in that Adam all dyed, for God and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111751:8"/>Chriſt was Sonne and borne there, and he became mortall in this nature, for God appeared there in weakneſſe, which weakneſſe is humility and lowlines of ſpirit, with all gentleneſſe and love; and when the wiſdome of the fleſh (the ſerpents ſubtilty) had opened natures eyes to pride and high mindedneſſe, and to wrath, covetouſneſſe and envie, which eyes is the ſerpents eyes, which is the evill eyes or the Devils, which the nature or man lookt through, which made him thinke that this high mindedneſſe and pride, with ſelfe-will, was a glorious tree, and that there was glorious fruit on it, and that it would elevate him highly, and that he ſhould be his owne God and ruler, and that he ſhould know good and evill which he did by wofull experience, taſte of its good which had the evill in it, for it was full of confuſion as was ſaid before, and was the mans toyle: but he thought it was a glorious fruit, and much to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and ſo doe all men that are in the firſt creation, and firſt world: ſo when Man had taſted of pride, high mindedneſſe, and ſelfe-will (the forbidden fruit) he deſpiſed God which is humility and lowlineſſe of ſpirit and meekneſſe, and was a ſhamed of this, and thought it fooliſhneſſe, to bee humble, meeke and lowly, for hee thought this to bee poore beggarly nakedneſſe, and was aſhamed of ſuch a lowly and beggarly minde as he thought it to be, ſo he covered this meek and lowly ſpirit with his lofty high mindedneſſe, and ſo the divine, gentle and holy nature is in hell under this filthy covering; and this is the covering upon God and Man, and is the partition wall betwixt them, and ſo man hath made the Devill god and lord of all, and hath given all that was given him into his hands, ſo God in man is in the Devils power, and he reigns as King and Lord of all in this firſt world or creation that is fallen into the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills hards by mans will that gave it him: for God gave man himſelf and all, and man delivered, and gave or ſold him to the Devill; for nature in the firſt creation is a Judas that is raiſed up to deſtruction, and is the ſon of perdition that ſells the innocent life in him, and afterward he hangs and deſtroyes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and puts himſelfe wholly into the Devils hands, and in the end of time when the man is weary of this wicked world with all his ſoule and minde, and will, wholly returne all into the hands of God againe, hee takes all upon him with his mighty power and ſword that ſtands in juſtice hands, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems himſelfe and the man out of the Devils hands, for he comes to redeem himſelfe the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael, which was loſt and hid in man, and covered with mans ſinnes. Now this holy and mighty power taketh all upon him for he becomes our firſt borne Eſau, Adam or Edome, and will bee our firſt world that is fallen, and will ſuffer with us and for us, as if he had dore all out ſinnes, for when be hath our man of ſinne on him he gives the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity power to indure this juſtice of the death of God for his ſinnes, and this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111751:8"/>ſword of juſtice and Gods death doth deſtroy death, and this death or ſword of God that frights and feares the man, is the beginning of the wiſdome of God in him to deſtroy ſinne, for the man in his firſt appearance deſtroyed the Lambe of God or good, and then he and the Devill, the wiſdome of the fleſh rule all in all in him till the man is weary of himſelfe, and deſires this death of God to helpe him, and this death of God is his backe parts that made Moſes face to ſhine, for the wrath, anger and frownes of God (which is his backe parts) is better for the man then the Devills face or ſmiles; and Gods death is better for the man then the Devills life, and his hell better then his heaven; for it is better to be in the houſe of mourning, then to heare the ſong of fools, though man in his off fallen eſtate thinks it not ſo: but this death and morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of God (which is his backe parts) doth make our face ſhine, for no man ſhall ſee his face &amp; live, nor ſhall or can we ſee his face, glorious countenance, and cheerfull ſmiles till our man of ſinne is deſtroyed and rooted out, and we returne to our duſt as we were before, and in ſilence with God againe; and ſo this death and mortality of God (which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his angry frowns and the wrath of the Lambe that takes away the ſinnes of our wicked world) is entered into our Eſau or Adam (which is the veſſells of wrath prepared for deſtruction) and is become our fleſh which is dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes; and this death of God doth deſtroy us which is death, for this Eſau with the death and wrath of God is a hunter, and doth kill meat or veniſon for his fathers ſupper, which veniſon is the wilde and heatheniſh brutiall man whoſe death ſhall reconcile us to God againe: for in the fifth of the Rom. he ſaith, that we are reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to God by the death of Chriſt, which death hath mortified us and killed our man of ſinne, ſo this death hath given us power by his death to deſtroy, kill and mortifie ourſelves, for this Chriſt after the fleſh or death, was it that lay under our earthly beeing, and ſaid, that he was a worme and no man, and that the great Bulls of Baſhan gaped upon him to devoure him, which was our ſinnes, and that the great water floods and ſeas of our ſinnes run over him, and he lay ſtill, and the man of ſin thought that he had been aſleepe or dead, and did not ſee their evill workes, but he made this darkneſſe (or darke man) his hiding place, and ſo he ſaw and heard all his evill workes; for he ſaith, I create light, and I create darkneſſe, that is that, I ſet forth my ſelfe which is light, and I ſet forth man which is darkneſſe, and he regards not me, nor my light, becauſe his deeds are evill, and ſo I am hid in his darkneſſe; but when the man is weary of himſelfe, then he ſeeketh for mee, and hath need of mee, though he thought I did not heare nor ſee him before, then he runs to me and cryeth, and ſaith, ariſe, O Lord, in mee, and thy enemies (which is my ſinnes) ſhall be ſcattered and rooted out in me; ſo this death or fleſh of God (which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111751:9"/>is death) deſtroyesman (which is death) in God in becomming his death or his fleſh, for in becomming the man of ſinne, he deſtroyes man which is ſinne and evill of himſelfe without this power of the holy Godhead, which holy power he hath given to the man to arraigne himſelfe before himſelfe, and to condemne himſelfe in himſelfe and to execute himſelfe, and ſo make an end of the whole man of ſinne, and ſo he becomes dead and buried with this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the holy Godhead, for it is better be dead with God, and to be at reſt with him, then to be alive with the Devill, and to be in torment in his hell: for this death of God is death to the ſinne (which ſinne is death) and ſhall raiſe us up into everlaſting immortality and raviſhing joyes of minde: for hee ſaith, that that which never eye ſaw, nor care heard, nor ever entred into the heart of wicked man (in his firſt creation) is now revealed to them that love him, and thoſe that are of the new borne creature, and the ſecond creation that love him, and are the men of God who are ruled and governed by him; for he ſaith, that the troubles and ſufferings which wee endure (in the cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the man of ſin in the former world) is not worthy of that joy and ſweet conſolation that we ſhall receive, and ſhall be given to us that hath taſted of the death of Chriſt, and hath gone through his ſufferings with him into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond world that is full of joy, for this end of Eſau (or Edom) is the end of the firſt creation, and the veſſell of wrath that hath ordained himſelfe to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and God foreknew that he would doe all theſe things to himſelfe, and gave him all in his hand that hee ſhould not complaine, and ſay he was tyed from any thing, ſo that he was free, and might have ſtood or fell; but he fell, and all Adams knows this, their owne conſcience accuſing them, for hee made man upright and ſhewed himſelfe to bee good, but he ſought out many inventions to deſtroy himſelfe, yet God hath mercy on him, and hath brought forth his elected ſeed to ſave him, which was Iſaac or Jacob, that wraſtled with God in this darke night of man to ſave and bleſſe him; for this Eſau was faine to ſell his birthright, and was ſo hungry with hunting and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the man of ſinne that he had almoſt loſt himſelfe, but his brothers pottage (which is love, and mercy, and power) was given him to ſtrengthen him to overcome the man of ſinne in himſelfe; yet he thought this pottage ſhould not have taken away his birthright and deſtroyed his firſt creation, which he wept for, although it was too late, for it was for his further good which is hid from his eyes for a time, and whilſt he is a hunting, for Jacob puts on Eſaus rough garment or fleſh (which is the law of ſin which made the man of ſin mad) and hee thought to deſtroy this Jacob, or this ſecond creation which appeared in the man; but in the end when ſinne is deſtroyed, they will be loving brothers, and one man of God, for this Jeſus Chriſt (or ſeed of promiſe the deſtroyer of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111751:9"/>ſin) will make all peace and quietneſſe, for this holy God is in Chriſt reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world to himſelfe (in mortifying and cleanſing this man, and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up all the chaffe of ſin with unquenſhable fire) that there might bee great love betwixt God and man againe, for this Jeſus was three dayes and three nights in the man of ſinne, and in the heart of the earth, and was carried into his wilderneſſed land, and was tempted of him, the manner whereof ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards be expreſſed; for he ſhewed Man all his filthineſſe, and how wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked he was and regardleſſe of God and goodneſſe, and this was the firſt day in him, and the night of that day was the death and wrath of God that appeared in the Man, which did te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rifie and feare him, and was the wounds of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that told him what he deſerved, and he threw downe himſelfe at Gods mercy; and the ſecond day or light God gave him true grace and ſorrow for his ſinnes, and the night of that day is that bloody fight in heaven betweene the Man of ſinne and God, and that terrible agony and ſweat of death was on the humanity; and the third day or reigne of Chriſt is that day that Chriſt ſhall reigne a thouſand yeares in Man with death, which day is that power of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long ſufferance that laſts till the Man of ſinne is rooted out, for a thouſand yeares is but as one day with the Lord, and one day in this ſuffering and reigne of Chriſt is as a thouſand years to the man; for he muſt reigne till all ſinne is ſubdued, and the night of that day all hell is broke looſe to torment the Man for a ſhort time, but this Almighty power gives the Man a ſtrong and victorious power that he fights with himſelfe and overcomes himſelfe and all his devilliſh crew, and ſo the wicked world is ended, and Man ſhall come into a happy condition: There are many that think that Chriſt will come and reigne a thouſand yeares here on earth perſonally, but they will be deceived, for they look and judge of the Scripture after the outward appearance, which is not righteous judgement, for we are to looke on it with a ſpirituall eye, and then ſhall we ſee it as it is, for the looking on it as a hiſtory (and not as it is a ſacred and holy myſtery) makes ſo many falſe Religions; for the birth of Chriſt in this elementary world was after a extraordinary manner, and not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ordinary manner of men, for he was not as the ſeed of man, nor did the Virgin Mary feele any manner of paine in bringing him forth (as the wiſe and learned hold) nor doth the Scripture make mention of her paine as they doe of others, as Rebeckah Iſaacs wife, and Rachel Jacobs wife, for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity is a ſpirit, and the humanity is a ſpirit, and the Divinity and the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity joyned together in conjunction as man and wife, is but one ſpirit, and ſpirits bring forth a ſpirit, and can doe no otherwiſe; for this Jeſus Chriſt is a Spirit, and is the Spirit and life of God that is ſowne in our hearts and ſpirits, which makes us cry, Abba Father, for he was and is a Spirit comming forth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111751:10"/>of God and man that were and is ſpirits, and that organicall body or figure that he ſeemed to be in (and to eat and drinke, and that he was like fleſh and blood) was as three Angells that appeared to Abraham, which he did dreſſe a kid for, who ſeemed to be men, and did eat and drinke with them as they thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo Chriſt ſeemed to be in that figure and fleſh of the man, but he was a reall ſpirit, for with that body he walked on the ſea, the which Peter could not doe with his heavy body, but did ſinke; and Chriſt did hide himſelfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times and could not be found, for he did walke in viſibly, and when they did leek him to deſtroy him they could not finde him till he pleaſed to give himſelf into their hands, and he could come with his body into any roome the doores being ſhut, as he did after the reſurrection come to his Diſciples, ſaying, Peace be unto you, and he did eat a broyled fiſh, and they knew him by eating and breaking of bread; and there is ſurely ſome ſecret myſtery in that, for when hee walked like a gardener they knew him not, but by breaking of bread; and Thomas would not beleeve that it was the body that was crucified (becauſe he could come through a chinke of the doore as he thought) till Chriſt ſhewed him the print of his nailes, after which, he ſaid, he beleeved becauſe hee ſaw thoſe things; but Chriſt ſaid to him, they were more bleſſed that beleeved and ſaw not, but beleeved and truſted in God without the death of Chriſt: for if we had beleeved and truſted in God, wee ſhould not have fallen and ſinned, but have been more bleſſed, for the whole had not had need of the Phyſitian: but we all have fallen, and need the death of Chriſt to make us whole againe, and we cannot beleeve till wee ſee the print of his death and nailes in our hearts and ſpirits, which he hath taken on him, and is now his humane nature; for his Godhead and humanity is in us, if Chriſt be in us, for he is whole Chriſt in us, God and man, nor can he be divided and be in part in us; and if he had a corporall body of clay (conſiſting of foure clements, made up of fleſh and blood as ours is) it were impoſſible, and againſt reaſon that he could be in us; therefore looke into the Scripture with ſpirituall eyes, for that Chriſt that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to have a body to be nailed on a coſſe was a ſpirit, and ſhewed to thee how he is nailed with thy ſins to patience and long ſufferance in thee which is death to him, for he grieveth and mourneth for thee; for we grieve the holy Spirit by whom we are ſealed and made the ſons of God, and we quench and put out the Spirit of God from us, and this is death or griefe and paine to God for us; for there is no death to any but grief and pain, and no life but joy and pleaſure, and ſweet content, for the ſoule is an eye, and is compoſed of joy and harmony, and deſires to flye into harmony which is God; and ſorrow and paine is a living death and dying life; nor know I any other life and death but theſe, though there is ſome other things that is called life, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111751:10"/>ſtirring and motion and the leaving the body is called death, and in forſaking any thing, I am ſaid to be dead to that, and that dead to me. The Sonne of God, Jeſus Chriſt was and is a Spirit, God and man, which now doth live and walke amongſt us, and we doe really kill and crucifie him every day to ourſelves, and the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt which he would have us eat and drinke, was not ſuch fleſh and bloud as ours is; but there were then ſome that followed Chriſt as fooliſh as we are now, that when Chriſt ſpoke theſe words they did leave him, for they thought he meant they ſhould eat this ſigure or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan that he ſeemed to be in when he was a Spirit. The fleſh of Chriſt which he would have us eat is his bloud and paſſion, which is the death and mortifying of our ſinfull fleſh; which St. Paul ſaith, ſo long as he lived in he could not pleaſe God: ſo Chriſt would have us eat his fleſh and drinke his bloud, and joyne our ſinfull fleſh to his fleſh; ſo his death or fleſh, doth deſtroy our death or ſinfull fleſh; and ſo that death of Chriſt doth ſave us, and reconcile us to God again. Now I know no other fleſh of Chriſt but this fleſh which is the new and living way, is the curtaine and vaile before the moſt holy place, and all that will be ſaved muſt enter through this vaile; and when this vaile or fleſh or death hath done the worke he came for, hee muſt be taken out of the way, for no fleſh and bloud that is death, can enter into the Kingdome of Heaven; therefore when we enter into the moſt holy place, the vaile or fleſh of Chriſt is rent in twaine from the top to the bottome, and ſo the death and fleſh of Chriſt is finiſhed and ceaſeth, and he is taken out of the way; for there is no mourning, nor wayling in the moſt holy place, for all teares are wiped from our eyes. Now he ſaith, that he (Chriſt after the fleſh) muſt be taken out of the way, or elſe the comforter will not come, which is the life and raviſhing joy of Chriſt: And Paul ſaith, though he knew Chriſt after the fleſh: now hee knew him ſo no more, as I ſhall ſpeake of all theſe things more at large in this booke. Now when Melchiſedeck appeared on the earth hee was without father and mother, and he ſeemed to Abraham to be a man, a Prieſt and King, and bleſſed him when he came from the ſlaughter of the Kings, which are the ſeven deadly ſinnes: This Melchiſedeck is that Chriſt that was before Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham; as it is ſaid, Before Abraham was, I am; and this Chriſt that appeared in the end of time, is that Melchiſedeck that was before Abraham, and that Elias that was carried up into Heaven in a fiery chariot with fiery horſes, which was a Spirit and the power of God, though he ſeemed to be a man of fleſh and bloud; for Elias is ſaid to be the power of God in man, and I beleeve that all mankinde (when they have put off this lower elementary body that is dead clay without Spirit) ſhall be like Chriſt: Melchiſedeck and Elias, which are ſpirits, and may aſſume any bodily likeneſſe as they were and did appeare in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111751:11"/>theſe lower elements: my reaſon is this, becauſe Samuell aſſumed the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his owne body, and came to the witch at Endor, and Moſes and Elias appeared to Peter and Chriſt on the Mount; ſo I beleeve any one may appear to their friends as many have, for there have many appeared that have beene killed in ſecret to diſcover their murthers, and many of the Saints appeared when Chriſt was crucified: certainly it was not their lower elementary bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of clay that appeared, but ſome aireall and ſpirituall body they aſſumed, which was the likeneſſe of their former and lower elementary bodies, and like unto Chriſts ſpirituall body that appeared like fleſh and was not fleſh but to our appearance, and that it might diſcover to us and tell us what we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally and in our intellectuall mau; and Chriſt called Lazarus his ſpirit, and made him appeare as if he had been in his former fleſh and blood; ſure theſe things muſt be ſo, or what did become of Lazarus, and where did hee recide before Chriſt opened Heaven gates; for it is ſaid, that he is the firſt that riſeth from the dead, and openeth heaven gates to all beleevers: we read that Elias raiſed a childe from death, and another when the Prophets dead body did touch his dead body, the dead body of the Prophet did raiſe the dead, ſo the dead did raiſe the dead, which is a miracle; therefore there is ſome greater and further conſideration in it; for certainly they could not be dead, but this ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary body ſeemed to be dead, which was dead before (never being alive) although it ſeemed to be alive whilſt the ſpirit of man lived in it, as I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more at large in this booke; therefore let us conſider well how all theſe things can ſtand together with reaſon, or elſe wee ſhall make a confuſion of the holy written word of God that is given to lead us into all truth; for there muſt be a reaſon given where Lazarus and all the Saints were that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, whether they did dye againe, or where they now be; for wee never read of any thing they did on earth ſince; for it ſeemes they have ſeen the laſt day before it comes to us, and before it came to Chriſt; as the childe that was raiſed by Elias, and the dead man raiſed by the dead Prophet, and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus that was raiſed by Chriſt, as alſo a maid, where did they recide with their corporeall body of clay and elements till Chriſt did open heaven gates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſure therefore the man muſt be a ſpirit, and hath aſſumed and taken this body out of the foure elements, and caſting it off againe as a borrowed garment, and may aſſume a more rarified and aircall body to appeare in, as Chriſt, Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck, Samuell and Moſes, for nothing is impoſſible; only that may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to our darke eyes to be fleſh which is not, as the three Angells to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and to Lot; for we beleeve appearances to be that which they are not in deed and in truth (which we finde by wofull experience) the which makes ſuch contention, and cutting of throats about Religion; the cauſe of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111751:11"/>diſtraction is that we doe not ſee things with a righteous eye.</p>
            <p>I deſire all friends and readers, who doe read this booke, and all to whoſe hands it ſhall come, that you will looke into it rightly, and not conſtrue it amiſſe, but as it is really intended for the good of all; and where I ſpeak of the death of God, and Chriſt in man, I doe not meane that the Almighty and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull Godhead can dye or be loſt, but as he is dead and loſt to the man that deſpiſes truth and treads it under foot; and ſo I meane that God is dead and loſt, and the truth lyeth in the ſtreets of his heart (which is God, who is that truth) and the two witneſſes lye dead in the ſtreet of his heart unregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (which is mercy and righteous judgement and is God) which we ſhould have ſhewed forth to all the world, even mercy, and righteous judgement, but we have hid theſe witneſſes. So I deſire that the moſt holy and righteous God may be your guide and director to lead you into all truth.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The true Articles of the Chriſtian Faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Beleeve in God the Father Almighty, maker of the holy Heaven and earth in the man: I confeſſe and acknowledge that the ſame is a true holy living God or good, and that he is a mighty Spirit, and a perfect clear light that diſcovers to the man the reall truth of things, and how all things are in their places, and in or to the Man, and he is the reall beeing, the truth, light, life and love to the Man, and this is his name light, life and love, for he is all this to the man: for the love of God to the man was ſuch that he brought him under the law of diſcipline and correction, inſtructing him what to doe for his good, and convincing his conſcience for what hee hath done to himſelfe, and againſt God or goodneſſe; ſo he raiſeth up all our ſinnes as judges to condemne us for what we have done, and they correct or puniſh us, for God (or goodneſſe) hath put it in them to doe it, and God hath opened our eyes with his power to ſee it, which makes us hate and condemne our ſelves for what we have done, &amp; his holy power or light hath perſwaded our hearts to have true ſorrow and reall repentance for our ſins, with a broken and a contrite heart and ſorrowfull ſpirit, and ſo we begin to hate our ſelves and our ſins, and doe really forſake them, and doe confeſſe that we doe deſerve to bee for ever loſt and damned, and be deprived of God and goodneſſe for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have choſen hell, death and devill, and joyned our ſelves unto it; but Gods mercy and goodneſſe hath inlightned our hearts with his law, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111751:12"/>hath really corrected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for our ſin, and hath brought us to the beleefe of Jeſus Chriſt by his law or fatherly correction; for he receiveth no ſonne but whom he correcteth, and none comes to Jeſus Chriſt but whom the Father drawea to him, and this drawing to Jeſus Chriſt is by the law of diſcipline, and this law is the river Jordan or judgement, and Iohn the Baptiſt (or the light of Gods grace) that doth dip or dye us in the river Iordan or Iudgement of Gods glacious goodneſſe, and this his judgement doth cleanſe us from all our ſinnes that were as red as ſearled, and we come out as white as ſnow: and this is the firſt Baptiſme in the Fathers Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God or good, and that he is the reall ſubſtance of God, and that he is the goodneſſe that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from God or good: And I beleeve that all good things are made in the man by him and through him, and that all goodneſſe doth conſiſt in him, and proceedeth forth of him into the man, for his goodneſſe in us beareth in us our ſinnes by his mighty power of patience and long ſufferance, with grievous ſufferings and agonies which hee hath for our ſinnes, and there hee lyes or reignes in us till our ſinnes bee vanquiſhed or rooted out by this mighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of patience and long ſufferance; and when all our evill is overcome (by this power of his goodneſſe) then he delivers us (which is the Kingdome of God) to his Father that God may be all in all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I beleeve the Son of God or Righteouſneſſe, is borne of the holy virgin Mary; which virgine is the pure humanity, and this pure humanity is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed by the Angell Gabriell, or the power of the moſt higheſt God; and this Son or righteouſneſſe of God is begotten upon the humanity, and is the promiſed ſeed to the man, which is borne for a bleſſing to all generations of man, as was promiſed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I beleeve that this holy ſeed of bleſſing, the Sonne of God, Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of us, hath ſuffered death under Pontius Pilate the law of ſinne in us, and that he dyeth for and to ſinne in us, and is dead and buried, and in hell under our earthly beeing and man of ſin: and he ſuffers for our ſin in this hell, for they be all upon him, and he is nailed to the croſſe of patience to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all the reproaches and blaſphemies, contempts and falſe defamations or accuſations for our ſinnes cauſe on him, and for the love of God and to us, hath taken us upon him that we ſhould ſuffer with him all our own reproaches, contempts and ſinnes to condemne us for doing them, and that wee ſhould condemne and forſake them, and be dead to them, and they to us, by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Ieſus Chriſt that ſaveth us in us; and this is the baptiſme of the Sonne, and is the fiery tryalls, or the baptiſme of fire with which he ſaveth his owne body or us, which is the humane nature that he hath taken on him to ſuffer
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111751:12"/>for and with, and that it might be ſaved through him, and by his power in us, and whoſoever doth not ſuffer this death with Chriſt for their ſinnes, that is, to ſuffer under the law of ſinne (death for ſinne and to ſinne) the death of the croſſe, which is the patience and long ſufferance of Chriſt to the killing of ſinne in us, he is no Chriſtian; let him brag how much he will of his Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, till he hath taſted the death and life of Chriſt, and that all this is come to paſſe in him; for they muſt all taſte of this cup or paſſion, and be baptiſed with his baptiſme: for if we doe not ſuffer and dye with him, we ſhall never riſe and reigne with him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I beleeve that the holy God, hath raiſed up his Sonne Jeſus from the dead, and that he was three dayes and three nights in hell under the earthly man of ſinne, and in the heart of his earthly being; and the firſt day he ſheweth and diſcovereth unto man his ſins, and the night of the day doth terrifie and wound the conſcience, and doth feare the man which is the law of ſin, or the wrath of God upon the man that ſinneth. And the ſecond day is the grace and power of God, which giveth the true ſorrow and repentance for thy ſins; and the night of that day, is that bloudy fight, in which is the ſweat and agony of death in thee that crucifies and kills thee for thy ſins. And the third day is the power of Chriſt that gives thee victory over death, devill, hell and ſins, ſo that thou art dead unto ſin; and the night of this day is the patience and long ſufferance of Chriſt in thee till thou haſt overcome the evill one; for in this day and night is the whole myſtery of Chriſt finiſhed, and the Son of God is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thee, and thou becommeſt dead and buried in him, and he in thee, ſo the laſt day is comming on to thee which is the reſurrection of Chriſt in thee, and with thee, which is the new creature, or man of God, Jeſus Chriſt, which was dead in thee, and with thee, and when you have ſuffered together, you ſhall reigne together in perpetuall joyes with him in God, for ever, and for ever.</p>
               <p>I beleeve that this Jeſus, or our Saviour, is aſcended up to his Father, and doth carry them up that have ſuffered with him, and hath cleanſed them, and prepared them a Kingdome for his Father, that God may be all in all in us, for he, Chriſt after the fleſh (which is death and mortification) muſt reigne in us till all ſin be ſubdued, and then he delivers, us up to his Father: for he ſaith, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we eat his fleſh and drinke his bloud there is no life in us; therefore let us eat this fleſh and drinke this blood of mortification, and killing and crucifying our ſins: This was the fleſh of Chriſt that St. Paul ſpake of, ſaying, though he knew Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now he knew him ſo no more: O that we had all eaten this ſupper of Chriſt, then were we happy, but till then moſt unhappy; for we muſt drinke this cup or paſſion, and ſhew the Lords death till he come in his life and glory.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111751:13"/>
               <p n="7">7. I beleeve that Ieſus ſhall come from the ſtrength or right hand of God with all his Saints or Angels, or the good motions which are thouſands of them, and they with Chriſt ſhall judge the quick and dead in us, which quick is himſelfe and all his Saints and holy Angells to live, reigne and dwell in us, and judge the dead ſins never to live any more in us, but be damned and loſt for ever out of us: ſo this is the laſt day or light, or day of righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſhall laſt for ever in us. O that it were ſo come to paſſe in all, and that they might ſee this laſt and everlaſting day or new day, which ſhall laſt for ever and for ever.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I beleeve in the Holy Ghoſt, and that he is the ancient of dayes, and is the love of the Father and of the Son, which is the reciprocall love of ſinging one to one, and this holy love or Holy Ghoſt hath joyned God and man toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and hath pulled downe all partition walls that hindered their comming together, and hath baptized or dipt or dyed the man in this his moſt holy life or holy ſpirit, and hath made him a holy houſe, Church or Temple for God to live and dwell in, and Chriſt is the head ſtone or foundation of this moſt holy houſe. O that all men were become this Temple or houſe of God to dwell in.</p>
               <p n="9">9. I beleeve that there is one holy Church, and this Church are all holy men that are without ſinne, ſpot or wrinckle, for all holy men are the body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; that is, cleanſed by him and made pure, for hee is the head of a pure body, and there is no ſin in his body or Church, nor is he head of a ſinfull body, therefore looke to it you that are ſinfull men, for you are not the members of Chriſts body or Church of Chriſt, as you may ſee in the fifth of the Epheſians, where it is evident that he ſaith, that his body or Church is without ſin.</p>
               <p n="10">10. I beleeve that all ſinnes are forgiven in this Church, for Chriſt hath forgiven them the ſinnes that are paſt, and hath covered them with his holy life, ſo that thoſe evills ſhall never riſe againſt us more, but wee ſhall live and reigne over devill, death and hell with Chriſt for evermore, and ſit with him at Gods right hand for ever and for ever.</p>
               <p n="11">11. I beleeve the reſurrection of the fleſh of Chriſt that is joyned to the humanity, and this fleſh or death of Chriſt, with the humane nature ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe into immortality, and for this mortality of theirs, ſhall put on immortality, and all death ſhall be ſwallowed in victoriouſneſſe; ſo happy art thou, O man, that haſt put on the fleſh or mortality of Chriſt; for this fleſh or mortality ſhall carry thee into everlaſting immortality, and into everlaſting life and joy of holy minds.</p>
               <p n="12">12. I beleeve that there is but this one holy and everlaſting life, and this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111751:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>life is the holy life of God, and he hath choſen the man to live in it, and to her one with him for ever. Take it to heart, for this is the reall truth, and ſurely thou ſhalt finde it: ſo if thou ſeekeſt for it, thou ſhalt finde it, and it ſhall bee ſo unto thee.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> A deſcription of one ſpirit acting in all, which ſome affirme is God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow what a ſpirit is, is to be conſidered; for all things appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the man he gave them ſeverall names according to their natures, and as they appeared unto him; for in Gen. it is ſaid, that Adam the man, gave every thing and creature his name according as his nature was to the man, and it was ſo, and could bee no otherwayes; for the genius and wiſdome of God in man gave theſe ſeverall names by his inſpirations and lights which hee diſcovered to the man how the natures and qualities of things were, and they are really ſo, for they be named by the Spirit of God in man: but there are many cavellers that diſpute about it, and would deſtroy all order, and bring all into confuſion; for they ſay they cannot tell what a ſpirit is, nor what man or beaſt is, nor what fire, water, earth or aire is; yet they themſelves ſee all theſe ſeverall things, and their ſeverall natures and operations in them and to them; ſo that if theſe things had no name they muſt of neceſſity give them ſome name, or elſe all the world would be dumbe, and have no diſcourſe; for they could not diſcourſe of theſe ſeverall things (and their natures) unleſſe they had names to call them by that the one might underſtand the other, and know what ſubject they ſpeak of, and what each would have another to do; but theſe mad people love to confound themſelves.</p>
            <p>A ſpirit is that internall fire, life and motion of all things, as the ſpirit or fire, and life of herbes, and trees, which is named the negative ſpirit that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth it ſelfe to the world and all other ſpirits. Now there is another ſpirit or ſure that groweth and bloweth it ſelfe up into one organ, and feeleth any thing that toucheth it, and its name is the ſenſitative ſpirit. There is another
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111751:14"/>ſpirit, eye, light or fire, that groweth and bloweth it ſelfe up into an organ, whoſe name is called the rationall ſpirit or eye of capability and judgement, which diſcerneth all things in their order and place, and this is the man.</p>
            <p>And there is another ſpirit, eye, light or fire, that is a motion joyned to the man, that diſcovers the reall truth of all things to him for his good or hurt, and his name is called the ſpirit of wiſdome or God, and this is the light or right eye to the man, that foreſeeth all things for his good, if he will regard his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</p>
            <p>And there is another ſpirit, eye, light or fire, that is a motion that moves to the man that he feeleth in his intellectuall, which is the ſpirit and eye of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that looketh into all things for the mans harme, the which if hee looke through leads him into all folly and blindneſſe, and worketh him into all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; and this ſpirit is the deſtruction of the man, and bringeth him to all miſery and calamity; and this ſpirits name is called the Devill, the worker of miſchiefe; for theſe two ſpirits move to the man in his intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and he feedeth, ſeeth and heareth them internally, and diſcourſeth with them as two men diſcourſe and talke one with another, and theſe ſpirits are inſtrumentall to the man to perſwade him to what he ſhall doe, for he can do nothing but by theſe inſtruments, the one for his good, the other for his harm, and he taſting of both he knowes the difference, and how oppoſite the onces to the other, and how they change him and make him good or evill; for if any man doth good by the good inſtrument, hee that is ruled by the evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contradicts the good works of the good, and the good inſtrument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the man that is ruled by the evill inſtrument: but there bee ſome that ſay, the evill is good, and the good evill, which cannot be ſo; for the good is good ſtill to the man, and is one and the ſame for ever, and the evill is evill ſtill to the man, and is one and the ſame for ever; for if thou doſt evill to any man that evill is evill to thy ſelfe, and if that man that thou doeſt evill to, ſhould retort the like backe on thy ſelf, then thou wouldſt quickly be ſenſible that it is evill, and not call that evill good (falling upon thy ſelfe) which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon another thou didſt, call good: for if thou ſhouldſt vaſſallize any man, abuſe or ſtarve him, or cut off his limbs, and doe him all the harme thou couldſt, what good is this to thee? ſurely thy conſcience tells thee, it is evill and not good to thee; for thou doſt not like to have thoſe things done to thy ſelfe, for retorting and falling backe upon thy ſelfe thou findeſt it evill: So thou art evill and wicked. O man, whoſonver thou art that doſt thoſe things, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt another ſo to doe, for thou teacheſt him lies, that the evill is good, and the good evill, and thy owne conſcience condemnes thee in doing the evill,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111751:14"/>and ſo doth the conſcience of the others whom thou teacheſt ſo to doe, alſo defnding him with thy lies to deceive himſelfe with, for thou oughteſt not to doe any thing to any man that thou doſt not like to be done to thee, nor muſt thou doe that which thou wouldeſt not have done backe againe; for thou ſeeſt it is evill, ſay what thou wilt, to deceive thy ſelfe, for thou doſt coſen thy ſelfe with theſe vaine deluſions. Surely thoſe that are of the minde that one ſpirit acts in all, would (if it were not for ſeare of the laws of men) fall a cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one anothers throats, and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all miſchiefe being devills one to the other in their paſſion, for they will admit of no law of goodneſſe for their reſtraint. If but one man had this evill power to execute his will upon all the world for pleaſure then might it be thought to be good; but you ſee in all men a deſige to have their will, therefore thou muſt expect and it is juſt and fight according to thy deſert, that thou ſhouldeſt be killed for killing, and for ſtealing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore double, or be his ſervant to worke it out, and make double ſatisfaction for his loſſe and troubling him, for this is the law of ſin, and death for ſin, and this is in man and can be no other wife, for the evill that hee doth to another man riſeth up in judgement againſt him, by the other whom he bath wronged to retort the like backe upon him, for this law of ſin in the man ſaith, an eye for an eye, tooth for tooth, arme for arme, &amp;c. and ſo with the froward to be froward, and evill for evill, ſaith the law of ſinne in man, which is juſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward every man according to his owne evill workes: but thou cauſt not abide this law of ſinne, for thou wouldſt doe a great deale of miſchiefe and injury to other men, and take pleaſure in it, but that this pleaſure brings this ſting of death and paine backe againe to thee, which thou canſt not abide, ſo this thy God or pleaſure periſheth with the uſing, and change thy pleaſure into pain by falling backe upon thee. But thou wilt ſay, that if thou murthereſt a man in ſecret (ſo that none be private thereto but thy ſelfe) how can that murther be diſcovered, or the law of ſin be executed upon thee? I anſwer, that the law of ſin is in thy ſelf, and riſeth up in judgement againſt thee in condemning and wounding thy conſcience, ſo that thou art weary of thy life (and in the and diſcovers thy ſelfe) never being at quiet till the law of ſinne be executed upon thee; for we ſee few murthers that are long concealed: another queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be demanded, if this law of ſinne (which ſeemeth to be good or God, and is executed upon thee) is not murther and cruelty likewiſe: I anſwer it is, and is thy God and ruler (in thy off-fallen eſtate) that is a furious God and a conſuming fire, who will conſume thee in his wrath and in his ſore diſpleaſure, forthy ſinnes have raiſed up this furious God that holdeth thee in with a rough bit and bridle, whilſt thou art a wilde aſſe colt that ſtriveth to overthrow thy rider, and this cruell God ſhall be thy Lord, King and husband, and will tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111751:15"/>thee, ſo long as thou liveſt in thy ſinnes, and in thy heatheniſh nature, for thy ſinnes have ſold thee into his hands; as it is ſaid in the Theſſalonians, that thou haſt thruſt the holy God out of his roome or Temple, and wouldſt not receive the love of the truth, that is the reall good or God, and is true life and joy to the man, who is one and the ſame for ever, and is no change to the man, as the deluſive God is, for he ſeemeth to be good, or is not the God, nor reall good to the man for ever, as the moſt holy God is: for if we breake the Law or Commandements of this angry God, he is very cruell and jealous, and will make us drinke the curſed and bitter waters that ſhall make our belly ſwell, and our thigh to rot if we breake his Commandement, commit adultery or Idolatry againſt him, for hee it is that worketh this evill of puniſhment in our City, and is that cruell thundering voice that terrifieth us and makes our hearts to tremble: we would faine be at quiet with our ſinnes, and delight our ſelves with our wicked abominations; but this God doth ſo trouble us, that we cannot injoy our wicked ſelves, hee doth ſo torment us, and ſhall doe ſo ſtill till we are weary of our ſelves and ſinnes, and deſire to be freed from all, or to ſeek ſome way to pleaſe this furious God which wee by our ſinnes have raiſed up; for this law is added becauſe of the tranſgreſſions, and doth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue till ſinne endeth in us; but wee are not able of our ſelves alone to ſatisfie this ſevere God that is the ſtrong deluſion and conſuming fire (and is not the reall God or good to us, which we ſhall find in the ſecond world or creation) which now ſitteth in the Temple of God as God, and hath thruſt the reall holy God out of his roome, and is the juſt God that roigneth in the man of ſinne, being froward with the froward, rendering evill for evill, and is righteous with the righteous; for he is juſt in rewarding every one according to his workes; and although the man is ſo wicked that he cannot abide this judge, yet he ſhall be with this ſeeming God or good for ever, if he doe not hate and forſake himſelfe, and ſend for the mourning woman, and call and proclaime a faſt, and rent his heart and not his garments, which is an acceptable day to him, and ſeeke for the innocent Lamb to make ſatisfaction to this angry God, that he may overcome him with his innocent life; for when this innocent Lambe is borne in thee, he doth ſtrive and wreſtle with this ſevere God for thee, and doth overcome his wrath and evill with his goodneſſe; and if any do wrong him he doth not revenge, but doth good for evill, and ſo overcommeth this revenging God: he doth no wrong to offend this God, and when he hath wrong done him he will not become the evill God, or judge, to revenge evill, for evill: thus and in this manner doth he take away the linnes of the world and the law or puniſher of ſinne, and in taking away the cauſe, the effect cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth: but whilſt the crucifying the man of ſinne is a doing. it makes the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111751:15"/>in a great agony and bloudy ſweat in overcomming the ſinne and the wrathfull judge; and this is that moſt innocent Lambe which worketh all in all in us, and for us, and he is that ſtill and ſoft voice that lyeth in thy inmoſt ſelfe (and in the cave of thy earth) till thou ſeek, cry and call for him to ſave thee; therefore looke to it in time, and whilſt time doth laſt. What time is, and concerning man, I ſhall ſpeake more at large hereafter in this book. The ſpirit of man, and the two inſtrumentall ſpirits, is to bee ſeene and felt in the man and by the man, and is diſcerned by their ſeverall natures, the good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is juſtice with which the juſt doth juſtly; and prudence, with which the prudent doth uſe prudence; and fortitude, with which the ſtrong doth valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the good in heart; and temperance, with which the temperate walketh temperately; and faith, with which one beleeveth that to be true that they doe not underſtand, if they ſee reaſon for it; and hope, with which one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and confideth in that that is good; and charity, with which (having proper goods) he maketh them common to the good of another that needeth them; and patience, with which the patient overcommeth, and is not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; and piety, with which the pious condoleth the miſeries of another that is in miſery: ſo if thou art guided by theſe good vertues thou needſt not be afraid of the law ofſin, nor any thing elſe, for thy conſcience juſtifieth thee that thou doſt what thou wouldeſt have done to thee, and if any one is angry with thee for thy charity that thou uſeth to another, this evill flyeth in his own face and doth thee no hurt, for he condemneth the good hee would have done to him if he ſtood in need, and ſo he is a devill to himſelfe for condemning the good that thou doſt, for all evill flyeth in the faces of them that uſe it, ſo that none is ſo great an enemy to a man as himſelf: therefore thou art happy, ô man, whoſoever thou art, that is guided by the good ſpirit, for he is all good to thee, and the other is all evill: let it ſeem never ſo good to thee, yet thou ſhalt finde it ſo in the end, for his qualities are theſe: the firſt is avarice, with which the rich is poore and a begger, becauſe he knoweth not how to uſe his riches: and gluttony, with which the glutton is impriſoned, and is never free to injoy himſelfe in regard of his ſlavery to it: and leachery, with which the man uſeth the powers of his body unlawfully to his deſtruction: and pride, with which the proud man endeavours to be above all others, which is a lie and deceiveth him: and ſloth or negligence, with which the idle grieves at the good of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, and rejoyceth at their harme: and envy, with which the envious deſires unjuſtly the goods of another, which covetouſneſſe is Idolatry: and wrath or anger, with which the angry man bindes his owne liberty, ſo that he is not free but is a ſlave to wrath or paſſion: and lying or a lie, with which the liar ſpeaks againſt the truth, doing great miſchiefe in the world:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111751:16"/>and unconſtancie, with which the man is manifeſtly changeable, ſo that no good man dare truſt him: ſo thou mayeſt plainly ſee and diſcerne if thou wilt (for thy owne conſcience tells thee) which is the beſt of theſe two, thinke what thou wilt to deceive thy ſelfe, for none ſhall ſuffer for it but thy ſelf. This good inſtrument is the ten ſtringed inſtrument or harpe of David, on which he praiſed the Lord, and chaſed a way the envious evill ſpirit of Saul; and thy ſoule being an eye or light that is compoſed of harmony and joy, this inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is the moſt holy life) is given thee to ſound ſweet harmony to thy harmonious ſoule; for if thou ſound on the evill inſtrument of ten ſtrings, which inſtrument is that which was founded in Daniel before the Image, and made him be caſt into the Lions den, it raiſed up the moſt horrible ſound of thunder, lightning, and violent fire; ſo that if thy brutiall paſſions touch the mount where this ſound comes forth, he ſhall be ſhot through with a dart, for thy touching of this evill ten ſtringed inſtrument, hath raiſed up the moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God that is a conſuming fire, who turnes thy joyes into ſorrow and pain, ſo that thy life is now a living death, and a dying life, which thou ſhalt finde by wofull experience; for thou thinkeſt thou knoweſt not what of thy ſelfe, that thou art ſomething, and that thou cameſt from nothing, then by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thou art nothing, and to nothing muſt returne; ſo that thou art like a mad man that can give no reaſon of thy ſelfe from whence thou cameſt, and whither thou goeſt, and ſo doeſt what thou liſt and what ſeemeth beſt in thy owne eyes, although it bee never ſo much hurt to another man. O doſt not thou thinke that he that is the cauſe of thy appearance will take account of thy life, and of thy ſtewardſhip, and what thou haſt done here, whether good or bad, thy owne conſcience tells thee he will, therefore doe not deceive thy ſelfe with thy fallacies and deceits? Thou art that one ſpirit that is or may be acted in all, and thy ſpirit or eye is the great Abyſs of eternity, and thy eye doth or may looke in or through all eyes or worlds, whether good or evill, and if thou be joyned or looke through the evill eye, and art guided by that evill inſtrument, thou art moſt unhappy, and all that evill that is ſaid before falleth upon thee, and thou ſhalt or mayeſt for ever be with that evill eye or world, unleſſe thou deſire with all thy heart, ſoule and minde, to be changed and delivered out of this evill and wicked world; for it is thy will that hath damned thee by the evill inſtrument, and thy will ſaves thee by the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, for thou art paſſive, and mayeſt be carried by thy will to give thy ſelfe to what thou pleaſeſt, to bee carried or ruled by the good or by the evill, and thou canſt not be joyned to both at once; therefore thou muſt be dead to the evill, and the evill to thee, before thou canſt be joyned to the good to bee moved thereby. Now when thou art acted by the evill inſtrument, thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111751:16"/>evill good, and good evill; ſo that when thou thinkeſt it good, and takeſt pleaſure in doing wrong or miſchiefe to another, thou takeſt pleaſure in a lie, and thinkeſt that evill to be good, becauſe thou art not ſenſible, nor feeleſt the truth of the thing acted, but the fallacie, lie and deceit which deceiveth all mankinde; therefore all things are not to man as hee imagineth, for many imagine themſelves to be better then other men, as Kings, Lords, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who thinke themſelves great, taking pleaſure in the ſame, although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and truth there is no ſuch matter, for all men are alike and made of one mould; ſo that it may evidently appeare that they who doth thinke ſo, take pleaſure in a lie, and this ſeemeth to them to be good: this lie transformeth himſelfe into an Angell of light to be like the reall God or good, when indeed and truth, it is but a deluſion, and a joy or pleaſure which periſheth with the uſing; for the reall God or good is one and the ſame for ever, and no man or thing can take away that joy, for it continueth ſtill the ſame, being no change; but thou takeſt pleaſure in that which is nothing to thee, and grieveſt at that which is nothing to thee, ſo thy griefe and joy is lies; for when thou thinkeſt that to be to thee which is not reall indeed and in truth, thou deceiveſt thy owne ſoule, and none ſhall ſuffer for it but thy owne ſelfe: when thou a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt any man the action falleth upon him and he it is that feeleth it, and if the like action falleth upon thee thou feeleſt it in the ſame manner; for all actions of one kinde falleth alike to all that are paſſive or ſuffers, therefore deceive not thy ſelfe for thou that acteſt is one and he that ſuffers is another; and thou that acteth is not the other that ſuffereth; for that which is felt by the one is nothing to the other that feeleth not, for the paſſive and active are two, therefore doe not thou deceive thy ſelfe and take pleaſure in that which is paine to another, for in doing ſo thou joyeſt, whereas thou wouldeſt grieve if it did fall upon thy ſelfe; and if harme fall to any man we ſhould participate of his griefe as if it did befall us, and not rejoyce at anothers harme, for this is the deluſion of the Devill to rejoyce where is no cauſe of joy, but is his own imagined joy, which is a lie, and periſheth with the uſing; and to grieve where is no cauſe of griefe, is a deluſion and lie to torment our ſelves withall, as ſome doe torment themſelves that they have not ſo much means and riches as they would have, and ſuch honour and eſtimation as they would have, or to be ſo well or better thought of then others; and they grieve that they cannot doe as much miſchiefe as they intended to doe, and they grieve when any ſhews mercy or charity to another whom they hate, although they ſee that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand in need of his charity, and doth ſay that this action of charity is a Devill to that man that hated him, and God to him that received it, ſo making an action to be God or the Devill; canſt not thou diſcerne the fallacie and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111751:17"/>lie here? is this charity any thing to thee ſeeing thou didſt not receive it? if it had been to thee, and thou hadſt received the ſame, it had beene as good to thee as to him, for all things fall alike to all as was ſaid before: therefore thou rejoyceſt at thou knoweſt not what till thou feeleſt the ſame, and ſeeſt where the fallacie lyes: wherefore when thou diſcerneſt the fallacie, thou mayeſt ſee that thou oughteſt to be glad when any good commeth to another as if it had come to thy ſelfe; for nature tells us, that we ſhould make every mans caſe our owne: and the Scripture ſpeaketh (without exception) ſaying, Rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and receive good, and grieve with them that grieve or receive hurt or harme; but to grieve at another mans joy or good, is the Devill that grieveth where no cauſe of griefe is; for in grieving at the other mans joy hee imagineth a lie (which is not the truth of that joy in the other man) ſo tormenting himſelfe with that which is not, for if that joy of the other were in thee it could not be griefe, but thou deludeſt thy ſelfe when thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt anothers griefe thy joy, or his joy thy griefe, and ſo thy faith or beleefe is that that is not, but is a lie, for joy is not griefe, nor griefe joy; but thou doſt deceive thy ſelfe in ſaying anothers griefe is thy joy, or his joy thy griefe, for anothers joy or griefe can be nothing to thee in reallity, but by participation, and ſo it is thy joy or griefe, and no otherwayes, ſo that by participation, we rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and grieve with them that grieve, and when wee doe the contrary (as to grieve at anothers joy, or joy at his griefe) it is a deluſion of the Devill that maketh joy ſeem griefe, and griefe ſeem joy, by his deceitfull fallacies; and when thou ſhalt looke with a righteous and juſt eye, then thou ſhalt ſee all theſe fallacies and deceits, wherein thou haſt ſo willingly coſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed thy ſelfe to loſe thy owne ſoule: but thou thinkeſt thou canſt not loſe it, for thou thinkeſt thou art ſomething, and nothing, and it is no matter let every thing run which way it will, all things will be well at laſt, but thou art as greatly miſtaken in this, as thou art in the reſt, as thou ſhalt find by wofull experience when it falls upon thee, and it is as true as thou art, and that there is a God, that thou muſt anſwer for all that thou haſt done whether good or evill, to him that is the cauſe of thy appearance, think what thou wilt to deceive thy ſelfe. So thou thinkeſt alſo that all things elſe is ſomething and nothing, when ſomething is ſomething ſtill, for there is no ſuch thing as nothing, neither is there any demonſtration or words to expreſſe the ſame, therefore in ſaying thou knoweſt nothing, it is true ſo farre and in this manner, thou canſt not poſſibly know that that is not, but canſt know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and poſſibly all things if thou haſt to doe with all or ſome; for that that thou uſeſt and haſt to doe with all thou knoweſt its qualities, for all things hath quallities and quantities, and are to be knowne by the ſame; and as their qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111751:17"/>be, ſo are they called and named, for every thing hath its ſeverall quallity and ſo a ſeverall name, and thy owne eyes ſees theſe ſeverall things and their quallities, for thou ſeeſt the quallity of fire that it will conſume or burne any thing that is put in it, and ſome things it will melt, and harden others; ſo thou ſeeſt really what fire is by theſe quallities, and it is verily ſo and very true, and is no other thing then it ſhews it ſelfe to be: and the quallity of water is to moyſten and cleanſe, or to quench thirſt or fires, and many other things that I need not expreſſe, which is really ſo as it manifeſteth it ſelfe to all the world, and can be no other thing then as it is manifeſted: And the aires quallity is manifeſted by many ſeverall operations, for it makes the fire burne and ſet forth his quallity, and it deadneth and taketh away the life of many thing, and reviveth and refreſheth many things that walke in it, and many other opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of life and death it hath which I cannot expreſſe: And the earth hath divers ſetting forth of its quallities, as to make all ſeeds ſet forth themſelves in their ſhapes and formes, making them appeare to all the world: and all theſe ſeeds and herbes have their ſeverall quallities and ſetting forthof them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which thoſe who ſtudy nature can ſet forth and ſhew the reall truth of by their effects; for the leaſt herbe, tree or mettall, or any other living creature hath his ſeverall quallities, as the Galeniſt, Herbaliſt, or thoſe who ſtudy mineralls finde out; and thoſe Doctors and Phyſitians ſee the ſeverall qualli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of things with the antipathies and ſimpathies of their ſeverall quallities, and it is really ſo and they be the very ſame thing as they ſet themſelves forth to be, for their nature is really declared by theſe their quallities.</p>
            <p>Now every man and woman hath ſeverall quallities, and is proper ſelfe. and their quallities are either antipathies or ſimpathies one with another, for the natures of ſome are ſo oppoſite, and there is ſuch antipathy that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree nor abide to live one with the other, but in continuall oppoſition; and there are others whoſe natures and quallities doe ſympathize, and thoſe doe agree and live moſt happily together in ſweet ſociety: now every mans nature is as his complexion is, and is compoſed of the ſpirituall elements of earth, water, aire, and fire, which is the intellectuall and internall man: I doe not meane the earth, water, aire, and fire that is materiall (and thoſe lower elements which is a dead matter) but the intellectuall, internall and ſpirituall elements which are all ſpirit and life; for ſome men and women are compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded moſt of the ſpirituall element of fire, and they are more full of fury and wrath; and another is more compounded of aire, and hee is more amorous, ſweet and pleaſantly diſpoſed, and given more to the act of generation then any other, for his minde is full of ſpirits that would appeare by him; for the ſpirits of men and women doe more animate the aire all man then any other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111751:18"/>to make them appeare in this lower elementary world; the reaſon is, becauſe he is moſt flexible, and more eaſie to be moved by their inſtigation to bring them forth: and the flegmaticke man that is more compounded of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all waters is more dull, and his capacity cannot very ſoone reach or conceive any thing, but when he receives he will hardly loſe it againe, whether good or bad, therefore it is good for him to have his mind ſet upon the beſt object: and the man that is more compounded of the ſpirituall earth, he is of the moſt deep reaching minde of all, for he hath all the elements more powerfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted together in him, and he containes more of them then all the reſt, being more capatious; and if his minde be ſet upon the evill object the Devill, hee is the moſt wicked that is upon the earth, and the Devill can worke more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe by him then by all the reſt, for his capatious minde can ſooner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive miſchiefe (when it is ſhewed him) then all the reſt beſides, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill by him doth moſt prodigious and horrid cruelties, although hee doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and too much by all; for this wicked ſpirit through and by them all, ſets Kingdomes together by the eares, making one to kill another, perſwading them to take pleaſure in doing ſuch miſchiefe, but it is a mad pleaſure and wickedneſſe ſo to doe, and ſo it will be found in the end, let them thinke as well as they will of it for the preſent: ſometimes they ſet Countries on fire, conſuming all their victualls and corne, and this they take pleaſure in, but if rightly conſidered it is miſerable paine and madneſſe, for they themſelves come afterward to ſuffer ſuch miſery and want for their waſtefull ſpoyling and conſuming of things, that they ſtarve and dye for hunger, and are forced many times to eat one another, as may be ſeen and heard of where theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes are. If this be God or good that acteth thoſe things, and tells me that it is pleaſure, I will abandon ſuch a god as the moſt abominable and hatefull thing that is, and deſire to have nothing to doe with ſuch and abominable and wicked god that blindes my eye, and makes me thinke good to be evill, and evill good; for the Scripture faith, Woe to him that calleth evill good, and good evill, and light darkneſſe, and darkneſſe light; for wee are all ready to miſtake, but our nature and quallities cannot be altered, for we uſe our quallities and natures upon what object we light on, whether good or evill: For the cholericke man, whieh is moſt compoſed of fire, if he light upon the evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, he hath ſo many ſeverall temptations to wrath and anger, that his ſoule or himſelfe is never at quiet for one diſturbance or other, and many times in his wrath the Devill tempts him to kill a man, and he is in continuall vexations; ſo that he is in a living death and dying life, although he ſee it not, but loves this living death more then the everlaſting life which hath no bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe therein, but is full of all ſweet content, and all the workes that this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111751:18"/>life or ſpirit animates thee to doe, breeds thee no ſting, diſcontent or any thing to be repented off; but this evill inſtrument animates thee unto horrid and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell things full of miſchiefe, which cruelties riſeth up in thy conſcience and fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in thy face, making thee condemne thy ſelfe, ſaying, what a wicked man and beaſtlike wretched creature am I that doth ſuch wicked actions, I would not have ſuch things done to me, why would I doe thus to another? ſure there ſhall ſome heavy judgement fall upon mee, and I ſhall have the ſame meaſure met to me againe, and ſo ſtill the law of ſinne flyeth in the wicked mans face, and is called the law of God or the wrath of God, that moveth man to repent for the wickedneſſe he hath committed, and to condemne and arraigne himſelf at this barre of Gods judgement within himſelfe, which ſhews him all his ſins and wicked life, and ſo hee kills and crucifies himſelfe with theſe horrible wounds of conſcience in him, and is never at quiet, nor never ſhall till the cauſe is taken out of the way, which cauſe is the Devill and ſinne, and there muſt a greater power take away this death with another death (that is by the death of Chriſt being a death unto Devill and ſinne) which death is called the death of Chriſt in us, that ſighteth againſt our ſinnes and all our luſts and affections, and crucifieth all our ſin and ſinfull life, ſo that there is no more ſin, death and devill in us; for it is this death of Chriſt that deſtroyes the death for ſin, and the cauſe of ſin, which death of ſin was done by the law for ſin exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon ſinne ſo taking away the cauſe and the effect, which cauſe was the devill and ſin, and the effect was the law of ſinne; ſo that when the cauſe is taken away, of neceſſity the effect muſt ceaſe: and this death or mortality of Chriſt, ſhall raiſe us up into immortality; ſo that we may ſay, O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory? for the ſtrength of our ſins was the law of ſinne, which law or wounds of conſcience was our grave wherein we were dead and buried: ſo this death of Chriſt hath freed us from all deaths and mortallities, and his death and mortallity will bring us into the true ſweet and everlaſting life, which I deſire all ſoules may come into and injoy. Now he whoſe ſpirit is moſt compoſed of ſpirituall fire (as was ſaid before) when he was ruled by the evill inſtrument doing ſuch wrathfull and cruell things, when he is turned to God and goodneſſe, his quallity and nature of fire is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into burning zeale, ſo that he is on fire of love to doe all goodneſſe, and is never well but when he can doe ſome deeds of charity and love to others; ſo that his minde is ſwallowed up in God, and this his nature and quallity of fire is turned to all God or goodneſſe, for the Divine Nature is wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated in him; the which I deſire all fiery and choloricke men may attain unto.</p>
            <p>As for the ſpirituall ayreall or ſanguine man, if he ſets his nature or quallity
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111751:19"/>upon the evill inſtrument, hee is very laſcivious and given to leachery, gluttony, and drunkenneſſe, and to all vaine pleaſure which doth beſot the minde, for nothing doth beſot the minde ſo much as leachery and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all theſe his follies doe flye in his face, calling him foole and ſot, and it doth ſo beſot them to all good, that it makes them careles of wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and all other friends, and makes them apt only to deviſe a thouſand plots and miſchiefes to maintaine their beaſtly, brutiall and ſenſuall life, ſo that they ſpend all their owne eſtates and other mens, and in the end goe a begging or live upon others, and they defile and ſpoyle their owne bodies with the pox and other diſeaſes, ſo ſpoyling both body and minde with their ſenſuall living, for they are in an extaſio below themſelves, and raviſhed with a brutiall and ſenſuall life; and this their evill inſtrument (the Devill or unreaſonableneſſe) hath brought them to: and when they have loſt their organicall man, then commeth in their greater griefe or hell, becauſe they cannot execute their beaſtly and ſenſuall life; ſo they are tormented in that they cannot doe as they formerly did when they had a body here, for their minoe is upon nothing elſe but on their beaſtly, brutiall and ſenſuall life, which periſheth with the uſing, leaving them in great diſcontents; and the Devill ſets alwaies this joy and pleaſure before their eyes, and the want of their bodies to execute their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fooleries, which want torments them to the death, ſo that they are in a living death, and dying life, and the law of ſinne ſtill riſing out of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence condemneth them for what they have done, and for what they deſire, and ſo they are with death and hell, except they could returne: but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh of time, and of a day, and whilſt time doth laſt; and he ſaith, there is an appointed time, and after that time there is no time more, for in that time the death of Chriſt ſhould have taken away death and the cauſe of death, which is the Devill and ſinne, who hath brought them into this miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition under the law of ſinne and condemnation which is the ſecond death: for he ſaith, in dying thou ſhalt dye the death; ſo then all men of all quallities and complexions ſhall be in this condition for ever, except they bee amended by the death of Chriſt, for he is that innocent Lambe which taketh away the ſinnes of the world, and ſo maketh amends for all.</p>
            <p>Now when this ayreall or ſanguine man returneth, and is moved by the good inſtrument which is God, and doth wholly follow him, then doth God raviſh his minde with his ſweet contents and raviſhing joyes, ſo that his ſoule is taken off from all things below, and is never at quiet but in this ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation: for he ſings in minde, rejoycing in the ſpirit, ſo that his ſoule is wrapt up in God and goodneſſe, and hee ſheweth forth to all the world all love and goodneſſe, ſo that happy is that man that can injoy his company: I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111751:19"/>doe earneſtly wiſh that all ayreall or languine men or women, may ſet their minde upon the holy God that they may injoy this good, for their minde in this eſtate, is carried up in ſuch raptures in the holy God, that they live here below in this world as if they lived not.</p>
            <p>As for the phlegmaticke or ſpirituall watry man, which hath a dull and groſſe capacitie if he ſuffer his minde to be moved by the evill inſtrument, hee is ſo ſtrongly ſet on him that he will very difficultly leave him; and he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him live ſo lazily that he is good for nothing, and ſetteth his minde on all laſciviouſneſſe, on evill ſurmiſings and ſuſpitions, conſtrning all things in the worſt ſenſe, ſo that he is never at quiet for one ſuſpition or another, being in continuall miſtruſt of every one, becauſe his capacity is ſhallow, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath blinded his eyes with theſe fallacies, ſo that he thinketh every one to be his enemy; and he doth a great deale of miſchiefe in theſe his evill ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thinking to begin with others firſt, and in his blindneſſe of minde doth undoe himſelfe and others, and then riſeth up the law of ſinne in his minde tormenting him, accuſing him of what miſchiefe he hath done to others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other cauſe, ſave only his owne wrong apprehenſions, and ſo this law of ſinne condemnes and wounds him to the death, till the death of Chriſt takes away this death, and the cauſe of this death, which is the devilliſh deluſions, and the evill ſurmiſings which makes him do all this miſchiefe to others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe: And if this ſpirituall watry or phlegmatick man forſake the evill inſtrument with all his ſoule and minde, and returne to the holy God, or good inſtrument with his whole ſtrength and minde to bee joyned to and ruled thereby, then all his thoughts are ſet upon goodneſſe, and then doth hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct all things in the beſt ſenſe which is done to him, and he ſeeth all things that fall croſſe in this world, to be good for him, to wean and draw his love from earthly things which periſh with the uſing, and his minde is wholly ſwallowed up in God and goodneſſe, and all his thoughts and contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are upon God, and hee ſhe weth forth nothing in all his life but God and goodneſſe to the whole world, and to the ſonnes of men, for his life is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the moſt holy Godhead; if all the phlegmatick men and women were come to this eſtate, then were they happy, but till then moſt unhappy.</p>
            <p>And for the ſpirituall earthly or melancholly man, if hee joyne himſelfe to the evill inſtrument the Devill to be ruled thereby, he is wiſeſt of all in doing miſchiefe, for he hatha vaſt capacity and can receive all ſuggeſtions, and (as was ſaid formerly) by him is acted the greateſt cruelties, and therefore hee hath the greater wounds of conſcience; for the law of ſinne raiſeth up all his cruell deeds againſt him, ſo that his ſoule is heavily vexed unto the death, and he hath ſuch feare and dread in him, that he wiſheth that he had never been,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111751:20"/>for he hath ſuch fearfull and melancholy thoughts that every houre he feareth to be torne in peeces, and this is in him till the death of Chriſt takes away the cauſe, and then this wounding law of ſin will ceaſe: but many love their ſins too well to part with them, to let Chriſt take them away, and ſo they live and dye with them, ſo that the Devill and they are together for ever and for ever in his world which is without end; for the beginning of his world is the ending with the man, for the beginning and ending is with the man one and the ſame for ever; for as he was at firſt to him, ſo hee is the laſt and the ſame for ever, for he changeth not but continueth ſtill evill: therefore, O man, looke to it in time, and whilſt time doth laſt, for after one time there is no time more, and looke to it before the decree (where of the Prophet ſpeaketh) come forth, for after that decree is paſt, there is no hope; therefore looke to it whilſt it is called to day, and whilſt this day doth laſt in thee, which day is Jeſus Chriſt that commeth to help and ſave thee; but if thou doſt not regard this day or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, then the decree commeth forth to thee, which is the eternall black night of death and darkneſſe, which darkneſſe or night, is the depriving thee of Gods grace and comfort, for thou regardeſt it not when it was offered to thee, and ſo in deſpiſing it thou ſhalt bee for ever without it, thinke as much as thou wilt to the contrary; for as ſure as there is a God, and as thou liveſt, this will come to paſſe upon thee if thou doſt not looke to it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all theſe things come to paſſe in thee: ſo if this melancholy and earthly man forſake the Devill and evill one, and turne to God and goodneſſe, to bee joyned to and guided by him, he conceiveth more of the ſecret myſteries of God then all the reſt, for hee findeth out all the deepeſt myſteries, and all things are opened unto him; for as he hath ſuffered more, ſo more is revealed to him, and ſo God and he are joyned for ever in all love, and he is in everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting joy and comfort in God for ever and for ever. I wiſh that all ſpirituall earthly and melancholy men and women may bee joyned to this everlaſting joy and comfort.</p>
            <p>Where as I have ſpoken of the deluſive God in this Chapter, I deſire I may not be miſtaken, for the Scripture ſpeaketh of two Gods, the moſt holy God, and the wicked God of this world that blindeth the eyes of mankinde; one is the reall good, and the other is the reall evill. And the Scripture maketh mention of two Sathans, Devills or evills; and of two guiles or two deluſions; the one Sathan, guile, evill or deluſion, is for the good of the man; and the other Sathan, guile or deluſion is for his utter deſtruction; for the inceſtuous perſon was delivered to the good Sathan or evill, for the deſtruction of his ſin full fleſh, that his ſpirit or ſoule might be ſaved in the day of the Lord; and St. Paul tooke his diſciples with a good guile, and made them grieve and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111751:20"/>mourne, deceiving them by that godly ſorrow for their good. And in the Theſſa. it is ſaid, that God did ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve a lie, becauſe they would not receive the love of the truth. Now all the deluſions that God ſends to the man is for his good, and the deluſion is, that he worketh ſuch a beliefe and perſwaſion in the mans heart for the ſinnes cauſe, that he ſeemeth to the man to bee nothing elſe to him but wrath, fury, and deſtruction; and thus hee terrifieth man to make him forſake ſinne for his good, and to make him returne from his evill life: for whatſoever God doth too or for the man, it is for his reall good, whatſoever the man thinketh to the contrary; and it is juſt ſo, as if a father ſhould correct his childe for his good and future profit, although for the preſent it ſeem contrary to him; even ſo is man deluded by Gods fatherly diſcipline and law, till ſinne ceaſe in him, and then this rod, diſcipline or deluſion (which kept him in a we or fear to offend God) ſhall be taken away; that is to ſay, when ſinne wholly ceaſeth in him, and when he ceaſeth to offend God his Father any more: and this is the evill which is ſpoken of by the Prophet ſaying, Is there any evill in the city, and I the Lord have not done it? that is the evill of puniſhment. And that lying ſpirit ſpoken of in the Kings (that the Lord did ſend to be a deluder in the mouth of the falſe Propheſs) was ſent for a puniſhment to them, becauſe they would not believe the truth; and this is done to reclaime the man, and to let him ſee his errors, and that he may returne home againe to the reall truth: And againe it is ſaid, hee created the deſtroyer to deſtroy, and hath ſent forth the evill Angells with flaming fire, rendring vengeance to thoſe that will not know God. And it is ſaid in the Pſalmes by Davld, and in Job, That the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Almighty ſtucke faſt in him, all which evills, wraths, furies, or deluſions, is the law of ſinne which was added becauſe of the mans tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and they ſhall continue with him (as I have formerly ſaid) till ſin ceaſe in him: but God in himſelfe is none of all theſe, for he is a moſt pure and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, and is ſubject to no paſſions, but is a reall eſſence full of goodneſſe, neither is there any thing can change or diſturbe him: but the evill one tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth himſelfe into an Angell of light, to delude and deceive the man with his ſeeming goodneſſe for his hurt, loſſe and damnation: So the moſt holy God, by his miniſtering ſpirits aſſumes an Angell of darkneſſe, or taketh upon him the body of ſinne to deſtroy ſinne; and in the Scripture the Divinity is ſometimes ſaid to be Sathan in the deſtroying of ſinne, being evill, with the evill, and he is ſaid to be Lucifer the ſonne of the morning, or that morning ſtarre that is fallen in our hearts, for hee could fall no where elſe, and it muſt be hee that is that day or morning ſtarre that ſhall ariſe in our hearts againe: ſo wee muſt looke into the Scripture with a righteous eye, and conſider it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111751:21"/>rightly in its order and place, how all things hang and depend one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or elſe we ſhall loſe our ſelves, and confound the Scriptures, or forſake and negloſt them as many doe, becauſe they ſee many ſeeming contradictions not having the ſpirit of unity to reconcile or unite them together; for it ſpeaketh ſometimes, and in ſome caſes that man is paſſive, and God active, and that God is paſſive in ſome caſe, and man the active; and in ſome caſe it is ſaid that the Divinity ſuffers for ſinne and doth all in all, and ſometimes it is underſtood that the humanity ſuffers for ſinne; therefore if wee have not the ſpirit of the moſt holy Godhead, we cannot finde out the intricacies and ſecret myſteries of the ſpirit and minde of the holy written word, and how all things ſtand in their orders and places: for ſome things ſeeme ſtrange, as that God which is all goodnes ſhould deſtroy ſo many for Davids numbring the peoples and in one place of the Scripture it is ſaid, that God moved him to number the people, and in another place it is ſaid, that Sathan moved him to number them; and in the fifteenth of Jeremy it is ſaid, that he would deſtroy ſo many with ſeverall deaths for the ſinnes of Manaſſes: ſo that the Prophet Jer. was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and ſaid, that the Lord ſeemed to him to be a liar, becauſe hee thought theſe things ſeemed ſtrange to him to come forth of goodneſſe; but all theſe things are ſecret myſteries bidden from all ſinfull fleſh and bloud, and none ſhall ſee them aright but thoſe which have ceaſed from ſinne; for God and man have been for ever together, and they both have appeared in time to each other, and in this time there hath beene a partition wall let in by the man which hath parted their union of love, ſo that the man ſeemeth to fight againſt God and goodneſſe, and God fighteth againſt man and his evilneſſe, and nothing can be diſcerned rightly by the man till the partition wall of ſin be pulled downe; ſo in the end of time that holy Jeſus the Sonne of God pulleth down all partition walls that have made the diviſions betwixt God and man, and he uniteth them againe in all lovely unity.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111751:21"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A deſcription of the Scripture according to the hiſtory and myſtery thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OSES hath ſpoken of the Creation of the World, and certainly it cannot bee that he meaneth this externall world; for I could never heare any true reaſons that can bee given to prove the ſame, for it ſtands at one ſtay, and the Sunne, Moone, and Starres keepe one courſe; and the Sea runs her race up and down, and they ſtill are one and the ſame in their orders and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; neither doe they increaſe or decreaſe to or from what they firſt ſeemed to be unto man, nor doe they wax old as a garment, nor as the creatures which we ſee appeare that have a beginning and ending; for we ſee every ſpirit that appeares here hath a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted body which increaſeth and is diminiſhed, and is gone againe and is ſeene no more: but this externall world is one and the ſame for ever, for any thing I could ſee or heare to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The greateſt multitude of men beleeve it to bee created of nothing, but I cannot ſee nor heare any reaſon for the ſame, becauſe that of nothing can come nothing; then what muſt it be made off? for ſure it cannot be made of the moſt holy God as ſome do imagine and ſay, that there was nothing before but God, and therefore of neceſſity (if it be as they alleadge) he muſt make all things of himſelfe, but it cannot ſtand with reaſon that out of one ſhould come ſo many antipathies; therefore without all queſtion the moſt holy Godhead that is one is of a more pure and excellent nature then theſe lower changeable elements of earth, water, ayre, and fire, of which this lower world is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed off; for this lower world bringeth forth nothing but his owne nature, as earth, water, aire and its ſpirit of fire, from which all ſpirits have borrowed a body which they cannot keep for ever, becauſe its nature is changeable and runneth or whirling round, never ſtanding at one certaine ſtay; for the Sunne (which is ſoule, fire or life of this world) never ſtandeth ſtill but every yeare runneth his race round, and in his running he melts, hardens, congeales, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111751:22"/>and makes grow green, ſo that there is a continuall death and reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction every yeare of things under the Sunne; for nothing ſtands at one ſtay but is in continuall motion and change, and in this change is, was, and ſhall be one and the ſame for ever; for no man can conſume, diminiſh, or annihilate the leaſt atom or duſt, or bring any thing that is to nothing, neither can any man finde the beginning or end of things; but thou haſt borrowed a garment or body which did lye potentially in that matter, and when thou makeſt it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, it is ſaid to be a beginning to thee, and when thou leaveſt it as it was, it is called an ending to thee: As for the world whereof Moſes ſpeaketh (that the moſt holy God made) certaine it is ſome more excellent, better, or purer world for man to live in then this: for hee hath no true content here in this world or body of clay; for this world is the viſible God or good that is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall change, but in the inviſible world or inviſible God is no change nor ſhadow of turning, but is one and the ſame for ever: if thou borrow a body or garment of this internall and inviſible world, he never looketh for it again, for he is the righteous that lendeth never looking for it againe. O that all ſoules did keep this body or garment that was given them out of this internall world, that they might ſee with thoſe eyes the Sun, Moon, and all the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous orders of Starres, which glorious world is for thee, O man, therefore look for thy internall garment that is given thee for ever; for the eyes or lights of this body ſhall never wax dimne, but in thoſe lights or eyes we ſhall ſee and behold the eternall eye or light from whence thoſe our eyes or lights came, which ſhall be our everlaſting body that wee need not feare loſing or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, for it continues one and the ſame for ever, being the free gift of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God.</p>
            <p>There is a time wherein it ſeemeth to us that we had a beginning to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and inviſible body, although indeed and in truth this body hath neither beginning nor ending, becauſe it lay potentially hid in God and in his eſſence, for its beginning to us is its ending, becauſe the beginning reacheth unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and we ſhall for ever have this body if we doe not loſe and diſregard it, as I feare we all have done; for wee have not remembred our Creator in theſe dayes of our youth, before our evill dayes came, wherein we have had no pleaſure; for our evill dayes is this, when we diſregrad this holy body, and then thoſe eyes begin to wax dim in us, though in themſelves they are one and the ſame for ever; and thoſe grinders ceaſe from eating the internall life, the food of our ſoules, and the mourners ſhall carry this dead body about the ſtreets and walks of our hearts, mourning and grieving for us and for our great loſſe, and this is the grieving of the holy Spirit by whom we are ſealed &amp; made ſonnes of God; for we have quenched, crucified, and killed this holy body of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111751:22"/>the Lord which he gave us for a garment for ever to cover our nakedneſſe, and ſo he returnes to that holy divine earth from whence he came, and the ſoule, ſpirit, or life of that body, returnes to him that gave it. And now, O man, what ſhall we doe for our great loſſe? for we ſee nothing but death on every ſide, for this externall world is but a living death to us, for wee are in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall expectation to be called out of it; and beſides there is one that is worſe then death that followes us to cloath us with his mortall garments or body of wickedneſſe: for he prepareth a body which is a lie or deluſion, and ſhews us a body which is a lie or vanity to cloath us with, ſo that this body is worſe then death, for it is a living death, and dying life, and we were better to bee dead and (and if poſſible to be annihilated quite) then to live in ſuch a wicked body of ſinne and death: and it had beene better we had never beene borne or brought forth in it, as Job ſaith, curſing the houre of his birth, and the day wherein he was borne, and wiſheth that he had dyed in the birth, and that he had never been ſeen in this wicked world; therefore we ſee many worlds, yet cannot ſee what reaſon man hath to believe that this externall world was ever made as he imagineth, ſeeing there will follow ſo many abſurdities on it; for what reaſon can be given that there was but one man and one woman at firſt, ſeeing there is blackmores or men, and white, and it is contrary to nature and impoſſible for a man naturally black or blackmore to bring forth a white, or a white to bring forth a blacke, and we ſee it ſo by experience? and when Cain killed Abel, the Lord being angry with him, ſaid, that he ſhould be a vagabond and runnagate; Cain anſwered, that his puniſhment was greater then he could beare, and if any man ſhould meet him he ſhould kill him, when there was none to kill him; for if there was but one man and woman created at firſt, there was but his father and he in the world; and afterward it is ſaid that hee went into the land of Nod, and tooke him a wife, who did inhabit that land, and what man was the father of his wife? how can all theſe things bee made good by the letter of the Scripture? or doe you thinke that there was a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall garden, or a tree whereon did grow the fruit of good and evill, or that a Serpent did goe up in the ſame to ſpeake to the woman? ſure it cannot ſtand with reaſon that it could be ſo, for it is ſaid that all the creatures did come to Adam, and he gave them names according to their natures: now it is contrary to the Serpents nature to ſpeake after the manner of men, unleſſe you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge that ſhe underſtood the language of the beaſts, and thought them wiſer then God, and reſolved to be ruled by them, which to me ſeems altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon, that the woman ſhould be ſo ignorant and irrationall, who was created rationall after the image of God to be ruler of all creatures: for at this day if a Serpent went up into a tree, and did ſpeake from thence to men and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111751:23"/>women, it would make them afraid in ſo much that they would not doe what he bid them: or doſt thou thinke that in Meſopotamia (a great way off beyond the ſeas) that there is a materiall garden wherein ſtandeth the tree of life, and the tree of knowledge of good and ill, both in one place, and an Angell ſtanding with a ſlickering ſword to keep the tree of life from the man; and that Adam and Hevah were caſt out of this garden (for harkening to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent) to till the earth, and that it ſhould bring forth nothing but thorns and thiſtles, all which in my judgement cannot ſtand with reaſon or truth? for the Scripture ſaith, that none ſhall be ſaved but thoſe who ſhall eat of the tree that is in the paradiſe of God: why then doe not all ſoules or men goe to looke for this paradiſe and garden of Eden to eat of this tree of life whereby they muſt be ſaved, for none can be ſaved without it? And why doe not all men and women goe to fight with this Angell that holdeth this ſword which keepeth them from the tree of life, and conſequently from ſalvation? I ſee none, nor heard I ever any that went to ſeek out this garden, Angell, nor tree of life: and ſo if the Scripture be to be underſtood according to the litterall ſenſe, or this a materiall garden, none can be ſaved becauſe the ſame hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been found out by any ſince the fall of Adam: and that earth which is ſaid to bring forth nothing but thornes and thiſtles, cannot be the externall earth, for we ſee it bringeth forth very good herbes, fruit and corne, fit for the uſe of the externall manhood, and but few thornes and thiſtles.</p>
            <p>Therefore, O man, looke not thou on the hiſtory of the Scripture, but upon the myſtery which is hidden ſince thy wicked world began, for theſe are all holy and ſacred myſteries which are hid from all fleſhly and ſinfull hearts, whoſe foreskin of ſin is before them as a partition wall: therefore, O man, let thy partition wall be pulled downe by the mighty power of God in thee, and let the foreskin of thy ſinfull fleſh bee cut off, and be thou plunged, dipped, dyed, or baptiſed in the moſt holy and divine nature, or in the moſt holy God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; for if thou goeſt into this river of Jordan or judgement as red as bloud with thy ſinnes, thou ſhalt come forth as white as ſnow, and then thou ſhalt ſee all theſe ſecret and holy myſteries which are revealed to perfect and juſt men, and to no other; for to the wicked and ſinfull men, it is a cloſed booke, and a dead letter, for S. Paul ſaith in the ſecond chap. of the ſecond to the Corinths, that he ſpeaketh the wiſdome of God to them that are perfect, for none can underſtand it but ſuch as are perfect and without ſinne, for to the wiſe of this world the wiſdome is fooliſhnes, and they laugh it to ſcorne, and thinke it meer madneſſe, as Felix did of Paul, ſaying, That too much learning had made him mad. O that all ſoules, had this fooliſhneſſe and madneſſe, it would be more pretious to them then all the wiſdomes and riches of this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111751:23"/>world, for the wiſdome of this world is earthly, ſenſuall, and divilliſh, all which periſh with the uſing; and the fooliſhneſſe and madneſſe of God (as men eſteem) is to us our right and perfect minde. O that all men were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the Father Son, and Holy Ghoſt, then ſhould they ſee things cleerly and never have more trouble in ſoule, then ſhould they know all good things, and all teares ſhould be wiped from their eyes, and be in everlaſting raviſhing joyes and ſweet content of minde.</p>
            <p>As for the ſeven Nations (that the Scripture maketh mention of) which ſhould be deſtroyed when their ſins were full, as the Amorites, Jebuſites, Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, &amp;c. it cannot be meant the deſtruction and killing of men, becauſe it is contrary to the nature of God and goodneſſe to be the cauſe of deſtruction, for he is the author and cauſe of all goodneſſe and preſervation; therefore wee ſhould be like God, to pray for them, and doe them all the good we can, and not deſtroy and kill them in their ſins, for we ſhould deale with them by the ſpirit of meekneſſe, and not ſend them to hell headlong, for wee know not how ſoon they may return to God &amp; goodneſſe: wherefore thoſe ſeven are the ſeven deadly ſinnes which have ſet themſelves forth as Nations in us, which when they are at the full in us, the Iſrael of God (Jeſus Chriſt) muſt come and deſtroy them out of us that the whole ſociety of God with Saints and Angells may dwell in us, and that our ſoule may be a land that floweth with milke and hony, and till all thoſe good things come to paſſe in us we are not ſaved.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid of Abrahams beeing commanded to kill his ſonne Iſaac (which is contrary to the law of nature and to God and goodneſſe to command him to kill his naturall ſon) there is ſome ſecret &amp; ſacred myſtery in it, for in this is ſet forth the whole paſſion of Chriſt; or Iſaac (or Jeſus Chriſt) is the promiſed ſeed which is brought forth in the Ancient of dayes, or in the end of time, and is the ſole and only joy of the man; and God to trye the man would have this ſole joy and life of the man to be brought to the ſacrifice, but the Divinity or holy life cannot dye (but as it may ſeeme to the man) but the ramme or humanity which was caught in the buſh of ſin, he muſt dye and bee ſacrificed for ſin, for all ſacrifices are for ſin, and the ſoule that ſinneth he muſt dye: wherefore we ſhould not looke on the Scripture as a hiſtory, but as a holy and ſecret myſtery: for in Gal. 4.24. it is ſaid, that by Hagar and Sarah is ſignified the two Teſtaments, and that their children are two ſeeds, the one fleſhly, and the other ſpirituall; and Jacob and Eſau that wreſtled in the womb are ſaid to be two Nations, the one ſpirituall, the other carnall: and the Scripture teſtifieth them to bee two worlds, which is meant the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth in man, and not as moſt imagine, that God ordained the one to damnation, and the other to ſalvation; and the Scripture witneſſeth plainly that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111751:24"/>thoſe are allegories, and to be underſtood as myſteries, or elſe we ſhall altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſorder and confound the Scripture, and this is the reaſon of ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions one fighting againſt the other: for the Scripture in the letter ſeemeth to contradict it ſelfe, ſo that if we have not the Spirit of God (which is above the Scripture) wee cannot underſtand one word or tittle thereof aright, and none can have that Spirit, but he that hath ceaſed from ſin.</p>
            <p>As for the drowning of the world and building of Noahs Arke ſo many cubits high and broad, as the Scripture ſpeaketh, it could not containe all the creatures in the world by couples and ſevens, and all their meats ſo long time, alſo it might be thought that God did inſpire &amp; move all the creatures to come to Noahs Ark to be ſaved, the which I deſire you to conſider of, and the many abſurdities that would fall upon it to be underſtood according to the letter, which cannot be agreeable to reaſon, but that there muſt be ſome higher my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in it; for the Scripture ſaith, that there was but eight perſons in the Ark, and that all the world was drowned ſave theſe eight; and preſently after he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of Kings and Kingdomes: I pray tell mee, from whence theſe Kings and Kingdomes came from in ſo ſhort a time? for we read how many of the children of Iſraell went into Egypt, and were there foure hundred yeares; marke their increaſe during that ſpace, and compare the times, and you ſhall ſee how many eight perſons could bring forth in ſo ſhort a time; for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Kingdome, and all the reſt of the Kingdomes muſt come from thoſe eight perſons, which they can never prove to have increaſed ſo many in ſo ſhort a time; for we read but of ſixty ſix perſons that came of Shem, betwixt his comming forth of the Arke, and their entring into Egypt, and their abode in Egypt was foure hundred and thirty yeares, the which in all that time did but increaſe to ſix hundred thouſand till the time they came out of Egypt again to go into the land of Canaan: therefore if you will compare thoſe things and exactly calculate the times, you will finde ſtrange contradictions in them; wherefore you muſt not look to the hiſtory of the Scripture but to the myſtery, for the deluge of Gods wrath muſt needs fall upon ſome other world then this externall, even the world of ſinne and iniquity, and drowns all their delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleaſures and marriages by his heavy judgement and law of ſinne that he executeth upon them many and divers wayes: but the holy and divine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood with all the beaſts (which are the paſſions and phantaſies of his minde) and the eight perſons (which are the five ſenſes, with the will, reaſon and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which is to rule and governe all theſe beaſts) are ſhut up in the Arke, Cheſt or Divinity of God while this deluge runs over the wicked world, and are preſerved in the ſame to bee brought forth as a new and heavenly Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111751:24"/>to a better and more divine world, which is the humanity to live in the Godhead, or the holy divine life. Likewiſe the hiſtory of Joſeph &amp; his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, is to be underſtood ſpiritually, for the twelve ſonnes of Jacob, with their father and mother, is the whole divinity and humanity joyned together, and Joſeph ſignifies the higheſt perfection or divinity, which was ſold into the hands of the wicked by his brethren which is the humanity with his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the wickedneſſe ſold him unto the luſt of the fleſh, which was Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphars wife, ſo that the luſts of the fleſh deſired to injoy the perfection to her luſt, will and deſires, as the Devill did to Chriſt, which this doth preſigurate, and he left this garment of fleſh (which hee ſeemed to be cloathed with) into her hands for a witneſſe againſt him that hee was with her: ſo the wicked luſts of the fleſh put this perfection or Joſeph in priſon, becauſe he would not conſent to her, and helyeth in this dungeon or hell under the fleſhly luſts of ſinne, till our Pharaoh (King of ignorance and ſervitude) begin to dream of all the miſeries and famines that is to come upon us; then Ioſeph or our perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſent for in haſte, to provide food for us in this our famiſhed land of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude and ignorance, where wee muſt ſell our ſelves under this perfection (who is as King and Lord in this land for a time) otherwiſe we cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nor preſerved; and after a ſmall time this Joſeph dyeth in the land of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude and ignorance, after whoſe death comes a cruell Pharaoh to reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee, who doth impoſe ſuch cruell and hard burdens and taskes on thee, which makes thee long and cry out for a Saviour; then comes the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull God with his mighty ſignes and wonders to helpe thee, plaguing thy wicked king of wickedneſſe in thee; and when all thoſe wonders and plagues are fulfilled upon thy king of ſervitude, thou muſt enter into a wilderneſſed land where is no comfort, carrying the dead bones of Joſeph (or thy dead per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) and in thy going thou muſt eat the paſcall lambe, or the ſupper of our Lord; which wilderneſſed land, is the whole paſſion and death of our Lord Jeſus, whereby thou muſt forſake the onions, garlike, fleſh pots, and all the pleaſant meats which thou cateſt of in the land of Egypt: and in walking through this wilderneſſe (or this death and paſſion of our Lord Ieſus) we are brought to the heavenly Ieruſalem, or City of God, wherein we ſhall reſt in all peace and ſweet content: I doe not deny the hiſtory or litterall ſenſe of the Scripture, but there is nothing therein profitable for me, ſave only the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and ſpirituall ſenſe. As for the ſacrifice in the old law, where mention is made of killing of bulls, rams, goats and lambs, ſure it cannot bee that the killing of theſe creatures could ever make ſatisfaction for ſinne; nor could the ſpeech of a Prieſt ſpeaking over the head of a goat, carry away ſinne into the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111751:25"/>wilderneſſe, as it is ſaid of the ſeape goat; but theſe are holy myſteries, and muſt be underſtood otherwiſe, and the chuſing of the Prieſts as that they ſhould have no impediment, as a lame leg, or one arme, or but one eye, and that their attire ſhould bee moſt glorious, with the breaſtplate of Urim and Thummim, and the Crown with writing upon it, and the pure white linnen, which to underſtand according to the hiſtory ſeemeth ſtrange for the Prieſts to weare ſuch babling things, but that all thoſe are myſteries.</p>
            <p>As for the ſacrifices which ſhould be without blemiſh (as the lambs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent doves, with the ſweet odours and perfumes) is this to offer up a moſt holy and upright life without ſpot or blemiſh of ſinne, which is his holy Son Ieſus in us, a ſacrifice moſt pleaſing in his ſight, for he careth not for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of bulls and rams, but this moſt holy body hath he choſen: O therefore, let us offer up this moſt holy body and pure life for an acceptable ſacrifies moſt pleaſing in his ſight; this holy life is the odours and ſweet perfumes, which ſweet ſavor deligh eth his noſtrills, and raviſheth his minde with moſt ſweet contents; and the divine humanity is the Prieſt that muſt offer up this moſt pure ſacrifice, for he muſt be a perfect man without the blemiſh of ſinne, and muſt wear the breaſtplate of judgement with Urim and Thummim, which is light and perfection, with the crowne of glory which is holineſſe to God, and be cloathed in white linnen which is a moſt pure and innocent life: and now you ſee that Prieſt, people, and ſacrifice muſt be pure and unſpotted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne having all perfection.</p>
            <p>As for the holy Arke which was builded by the free will offering of the people, and Moſes going up into the mountaine to the Lord for a paterne to ſhew the people that it might be builded with all their pretious ſtones, and fine ſilks for curtaines, and the drinking pots of gold, with the candleſticks, ſnuffers, and ſnuffing diſhes, and the mercy ſeat, with the Cherubins that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth up the mercy ſeat, and the holy and moſt holy place, with the curtaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the holy and moſt holy; and the Altar and hookes, the table and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, with Arons rod that budded, and the pot of manna, which to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as a hiſtory, that ſuch a glorious building was made to look upon is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me; for to looke or judge of it ſo is to looke according to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance which is not righteous judgement, for in this is to be ſeene the whole myſtery of the Godhead and the humanity; for in the holy place is the whole worke of the law, with the death and ſacrifices for ſinne for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, which death and ſacrifices is the Godhead and manhoed which lyeth upon the holy Alter, fire, wrath, croſſe or patience till the man of ſinne be deſtroyed and rooted out of us: And the golden candleſticks, with the lights in the holy place, is the law or grace that ſhineth from the morning till
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111751:25"/>the evening, or till ſinne is extinguiſhed and done away in us, and is the lights of Gods grace which is true repentance for ſinne, with a broken and contrite heart and ſorrowfull ſpirit, which ſhineth till all things are finiſhed, and then giveth up the ghoſt unto the Father from whence he came, and then the vaile or curtaine which ſtandeth in the moſt holy place is rent in twaine from the top to the bottome, which vaile is the fleſh and death of Chriſt, and is the new and living way, through which all muſt enter or elſe they cannot be ſaved, nor enter into the moſt holy or <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> where the mercy ſeat is held up by the Angells and Cherubins.</p>
            <p>Now when the Prieſthood which is the holy humanity, hath fulfilled the whole worke of the Law (the ſacrifice for ſinne in the holy place) then they put on all their holy garments and attires, and ſo enter into the moſt holy place with their bells or hymns that ſoundeth forth the praiſe of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally to God, and externally all good to men, for in this holy attire muſt he enter in the moſt holy place with odours and ſweet perfumes of a holy life, and the ſmoke of theſe odours, and perfumes of a holy life, aſcendeth to the mercies ſeat, and raviſheth the moſt holy Godhead, and then he imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him in his armes ſaying, Thou art my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed; and this is he that maketh us Kings and Prieſts to God, and giveth us himſelfe to be offered up for a ſacrifice to God his Father for us. O man, how great is the love of God to thee, that hee becommeth thee to ſave thee, and makes thee himſelfe for the great love he hath to thee? for in thy firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he created himſelfe in thee, and then there appeared unto thee foure worlds; firſt this externall world, whereof thou haſt borrowed a body or gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and knoweſt not how foone it ſhall be called for againe, for the world whitleth about and calleth for her owne againe, and there can be no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of any thing here, becauſe here is nothing but change and mortality; for this world of it ſelfe is death, but that the ſpirits that are in it is its life, ſo that this world is not worthy ſo much as to bee thought off, for it periſheth with the uſing as doth a garment, only it is good in this reſpect, becauſe wee could not know light but by darkneſſe, nor life but by death, nor immortallity but by mortallity; and the reaſon we were in obſcurity or in ſilence before wee could come here, is this, that there is one eternall increaſe of the ſeed of man, and they can but appeare in time here; for this externall world is time, and time is a running round, and there is no new thing here but as it is to me; for this materiall world doth neither increaſe nor decreaſe, but is one and the ſame for ever in its turning round, only it ſeemeth to me to increaſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, and ſo it is finite, and becauſe the ſeed of man is an eternall increaſe; and this world being one and the ſame may be called finite in this reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not matter enough for all ſpirits to have bodies or garments of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111751:26"/>at one time, and therefore ſome muſt goe before others can come, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to come are infinite, and this world is finite, becauſe of its materiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine, not increaſing but running round, ſo that which is called the body of one to day, may be called the body of another to morrow; for there is no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here, and all ſoules muſt ſtay their time till they can come here, and in their comming and being here is the time to ſee diſtinctions and all worlds, and if thou doe not looke about thee and ſee them here in this world of time (but be neglective of the time) thou hadſt better never have been born or brought forth in time, for this time vaniſheth away to thee and thou ſhalt bee ſeen no more; for when man is in honour and knows it not, he is like the brute beaſt that periſheth being without God in the world: therefore whilſt time doth laſt to us, let us looke about us and redeeme our miſpent time, and ſeek the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting good or reall true world that is beyond all time or change; and this is the divine world which God hath placed in thy heart, as is ſaid in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes the 3. and the world whereof Moſes ſpeaketh Gen. 1. and is the Angelicall world or paradiſe out of which the man had an Angelicall body which is but a part of Gods houſe, for God ſhewed himſelfe but in part, and this part he loſt, and in that part he was that great Lucifer or Angell that was the Sunne of the morning, or ſtarre that fell, and in falling fought againſt his Maker, or him that gave him that Angelicall body or world, in which the moſt holy world ſtood as a tree of life unſeen or untouched by the man, for he had more minde of the diabolicall world, for all worlds being opened to the man he deſires the evill and worſt of worlds deſiring to be free before his time, becauſe he could not abide the ſervanthood to till and dreſſe the garden of the Lord (which ſervanthood is the angelicall body or world, which is the ſervant of the Lord) but deſired to be as great as God himſelfe before his time, and ſo his pride threw him downe into the moſt loweſt world which is the diabolicall; ſo that his body is now the body of ſinne, death, and all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and beſides, he hath pulled downe the divine and moſt holy world up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as a judge with wrath and violent fire, and ſo hee ſtandeth ſtill over him till the man deſire to come forth againe out of the diabolicall world and returne with humility, true repentance and reall ſorrow for his ſin, and then the divine and moſt holy world doth worke this true reall death in mans heart, and deſcendeth into the hell of his heart (that is into the loweſt parts of his earth where the wrath of God is) and there pacifieth this wrathfull Iudge or God with his humility and true ſorrow for ſinne, by which ſorrow and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity he crucifies and deſtroyes all ſinne out of the man, and then he raiſeth him out of the loweſt world into the divineſt and moſt holy world; and this world is the ſecond creation that God maketh in man and is himſelfe which he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111751:26"/>in him, for in his comming he firſt humbleth and then exalteth the man; for the divine and moſt holy world in his comming downe into hell (or the moſt loweſt world to the man to ſave him) doth appeare in humility and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of ſpirit, very meeke and gentle, enduring patiently all that the law would have him ſuffer, and ſo teacheth and incorporateth this humility and lowlineſſe of ſpirit into the man that hath learned God, ſo that they twain are made one ſpirit; and this is the new creation of which David ſpeaketh, ſaying, Create in me a cleane heart, O God, and renue a right ſpirit in mee: this is that poore, humble, meek ſoule that lyeth in the duſt and ſeeth no help which ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſed up from thence to dignity, and ſhall ſit with Princes, which is to ſit with the moſt higheſt God; and he is the barren that ſhall beare, and bring forth the holy Godhead or divine life out of him.</p>
            <p>Now, O man, mayeſt thou ſee how great the love of God is to thee; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forſake all worlds for his ſake, becauſe he loveth thee ſo deerly, and look upon all things through his ſpirituall and holy eyes, and then ſhalt thou ſee things cleerly and as they are, and not eſteem of any thing above it ſelfe, nor above its owne deſerving. Wherefore wee muſt looke into the Scripture with thoſe holy eyes, or elſe we ſhall ſee nothing aright, or as it is.</p>
            <p>Now to looke upon all the hiſtories of the Prophets, Judges and Kings without thoſe divine and holy eyes, where through we ſee the holy myſtery of the ſame, it will appeare very ſtrange to us, and contrary to nature and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; as for example, that of Bilaams Aſſe ſpeaking to him, and Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar being turned to a Beaſt to eat graſſe with the Oxen till the dew of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven had wet him ſeven times; and the fiery furnace ſpoken of in Daniell, in which the three children were caſt, wherein they had no hurt, nor ſo much as their cloaths burned; and the great Image of braſſe, iron and clay, which is alſo ſpoken of in Daniell, with many other myſteries which ſetteth forth the creation, fall and reſtauration of man by the whole worke of the law, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his new creation: ſo that the whole hiſtory of the Scripture (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood) tendeth to thoſe things, but are illuſtrated and ſet forth many and divers wayes; therefore this worke of man is wonderfull, and would make an eternall diſcourſe in the minde of man to expreſſe himſelfe. And the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of David that he did kill a Lion and a Beare, and did kill Goliah, is the whole worke of the law to deſtroy the Devill and ſin out of the man; alſo he complaineth ſometimes that he is in the loweſt hell, and in a deepe pit, and that he is a worme and no man, and that he is in the deep waters and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſeas run over him, ſo that in all this he carries a double death which is to kill and be killed, for the whole worke of the law is to kill and bee killed; therefore the law (or David) cannot build a houſe for God to dwell in, for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111751:27"/>he ſaith that David or the law is a man of blood, and that he ſhould pull down all buildings of ſin, and deſtroy the enemies of the Lord, and prepare timber and ſtones hewed and cut for the houſe of the Lord, that there might bee no noiſe of the hammer, or of the worke mans tools; for the law of the Lord hews, cuts and prepares us for the houſe of the Lord before we are or can be ſet in, that there ſhould be no noiſe of hammer or worke mans tooles hewing or cutting, which hewing or cutting is the wounds of conſcience making a true ſorrow and mourning for ſinne, and when we are prepared and made li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtones and a ſpirituall houſe (Chriſt being the head and corner ſtone that upholdeth this houſe and holy building, and this whole houſe is covered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without with pure gold, that is with a moſt pure, holy and glorious life) then the moſt holy and wiſe Solomon (the wiſdome of the Godhead, the ſonne of David, or the law) enters in this moſt glorious houſe that ſhineth with his moſt bright and glorious rayes, and there he worſhips and adores this great and moſt holy Godhead, and there was and is continuall ſongs of Hallelujah, praiſe and thankſgiving to him that liveth for evermore: and without this houſe is the middle court where the peace offerings that was and is offered up to this moſt holy God, and was and is the fulfilling of the law by obedience in killing the man of ſinne, the which doth pacifie and reconcile us to God againe, that we may enter the Temple with this holy and wiſe Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to worſhip and ſing praiſes to the moſt glorious and moſt holy God. O that it were ſo well with all the ſoules of men, and that it were ſo come to paſſe in them, then were they happy, but till then moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</p>
            <p>Now to underſtand theſe buildings of the Temple and houſe of the Lord as a hiſtory, with all theſe glorious externall things, how that there were galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and chambers, and in thoſe roomes pictures of Angels and Cherubins, and that they did uphold the Arke and Alter, and that the ſame ſhould bee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered within and without with pure gold, and that the ſtones muſt be hewed and prepared before they were ſet in that there ſhould be no noiſe of the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or workmans toole: what is that to thee, O man, to read the hiſtory of theſe things? for all externall buildings muſt periſh with the uſing, and thou never the better for it; but looke thou into the myſtery thereof becauſe it concernes thy ſelfe, for this building is thee and God joyned together, and is the rocke Chriſt Jeſus, that living ſtone diſallowed of men, but choſen of God, and yee as living ſtones are joyned to him and made a ſpirituall houſe, and an holy Prieſthood to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifices to God by this holy Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord and only Saviour, that hath called us from death to life, and hath made us ſit with him in his holy place, that is in the moſt holy Father:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111751:27"/>therefore O man, ſeeke after this holy building, and let it be built in thee, for all the hyſtories of the Scripture is concerning thy ſelfe, thy falling, riſing, or ſomething that concerns thee or the holy Godhead; therefore thou oughteſt to looke into the ſcripture with a vigilant eye, and with due reſpect, for it is the true looking glaſſe which ſhowes thee in what condition thou art, and therefore read it not as thou doſt other hyſtories, but read it and take it to heart, and eſteeme it as it is the moſt holy and ſacred myſteries concerning the great and moſt powerfull Godhead and thy ſelfe, O man.</p>
            <p>And as for the Hyſtory of Ieſus Chriſt that he was borne in an Inn, and in a ſtable, betwixt an Oxe and an Aſſe, and laid in a Crach, and that the Inn was full and no roome in it but the ſtable, is a great myſtery, for this Inn is thy ſelfe O man, and the chambers of thy heart is full of thy ſinnes, the great Kings of thy earthly being, which is pride, vaine glory, hypocriſie, luſt, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wrath and ſelfe will: ſo that the chambers and roomes of thy heart are full of ſuch gueſts as theſe, and there was nor is no roome for the moſt holy life but in the worſt place of thy houſe, and thy <hi>Herod</hi> (or bloody mind) will not let him ly there, but ſeeketh to deſtroy and kill him, and ſo hee is carried away and hid in thee till thoſe be dead that ſeeke his life: Now when Chriſt (the holy divine nature) comes into our earthly Man of ſinne, hee hath not a place to lay or reſt his head on, but is ſought for by our ſinnes to bee deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for he ſayeth, <hi>the foxes</hi> (that are our worldly Paſſions) <hi>have holes, and the birds</hi> (that are our vain Phantaſies) <hi>have neſts, but bee hath not whereon to lay his head;</hi> Doeſt thou not ſee (O vain man) that the moſt holy and divine world or divine life is neglected of thee? and kept under thy earthly being, and he is in the moſt loweſt parts of thy earth, and under thy ſinfull manhood, hee is that moſt glorious and holy light that commeth into thy wicked world of ſinne, but thou art aſhamed of him, becauſe hee diſcovers thy deeds of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo thou putſt out this light and quencheſt this ſpirit, for thou loveſt the deeds of darkneſſe more then the works of light, therefore this light or holy life is carryed away by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> (the perfection and fountaine of Love) to the holy light, from whence he came, till all thy ſinne and iniquity which ſought his life is dead in thee, for the holy life cannot live in thee, till ſinne be dead and rooted out of thee.</p>
            <p>Now to looke upon Chriſt comming into this externall world, in ſuch a mean manner, his birth ſo low, and his condition ſo poore and diſpiſed, and ſought out by the Kings of the earth to bee deſtroyed, was becauſe they thought ſcorne that one of ſo poore and mean birth ſhould bee King of all the earth; And thou mayeſt ſee the myſtery of his comming into this world in ſo poore and diſpiſed manner, which is to ſhew thee how hee is in thy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111751:28"/>ſelfe and in thy internall world diſpiſed and ſought for to bee deſtroyed by thy finnes the great Kings of thy earthly being: therefore (O man) if thou readſt the hiſtory of the birth of Chriſt, and not look into the myſtery how much it concerns thee, thou art never the better for his comming; for his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall comming to the ſight of the world ſhall vaniſh away like a tale that is told, or a dreame that is ſeene no more: therefore O man looke into the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (and into the holy writ) with a diligent and circumſpect eye, and into thy ſelfe where is written the holy word to thy condemnation or to thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: compare thy ſelfe and the ſcripture together, and thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelfe there for it is the true reall lookeing glaſſe wherein thou mayeſt behold thy ſelfe; and thy owne ſoule or ſpirit is a witneſſe to thee, that it relates to thee thy ſelfe, and it ſpeaks the reall truth to thee in condemning or juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee, wherefore O man take it to heart, for thou needſt not no other wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the truth thereof but thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>As for Chriſts being led aſide by the ſpirit into the Wilderneſſe to bee tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted of the Devill, and that he faſted fourty dayes and fourty nights, and that he was ſet upon a Pinacle of the Temple, ſhewing him from thence all the Kingdoms of the earth in the twinckling of an eye, and that hee told him all the Kingdoms of the earth were his, for they were given him, and if hee would fall down and worſhip him they ſhould bee his; certainly this cannot be meant of the externall, for no mortall creature (taking on this elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body of clay) can ſubſiſt without foode ſo long, nor could it be that all the Kingdomes of the world were the Devills, for who did give them to him? nor can there bee any reaſon given, why or how hee could poſſible ſee all the Kingdomes of this world with his externall eyes at one time: for this world being imagined round, high and low, it is impoſſible that any externall eye ſhould ſee it at once: therefore O man looke to the myſtery thereof, for when this holy Jeſus is borne into us, this wicked ſpirit commeth to him, and ſeeing him cloathed with our fraile and weake nature thinking to overcome him, ſhewing him our barren and wilderneſſed nature wherein is no good thing for foode for him, ſo that hee muſt bee ſtarved if hee lived in it, therefore hee would have him obedient unto him and hee ſhould have all his honour king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and riches, but he did forſake them all as abhominable, and brought his owne foode or kingdome with him, for he liveth by the power and life of the Godhead from whence he came, and by this mighty power he makes this ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and barren ground of mans nature food for him to live of and with, for hee participates and liveth of both natures; the Godhead and the manhoode, and this Godhead and manhood being joyned together by a conjunction (or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall union) have betwixt them both brought forth Jeſus Chriſt the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111751:28"/>Sonne of God and Sonne of man, who is both God and man, and being in the wombe of the humanity, is nouriſhed and fed by the ſame as of his mother, for all children live of the mothers life and nature, and are fed by it: ſo this Ieſus Chriſt comes into our barren ground, and by his mighty power maketh it fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till and fruitfull, bringing forth himſelfe in us, to live of us, and we by him, for our barren ground is plowed up by the law of God, and all the thornes and thiſtles which is our ſinnes, is plucked up and throwne away, that this holy ſeed may be ſowed in our hearts in place of our ſinnes, and this ſeed is a tender plant: wherefore, O man, look diligently to it, and weed up all things that is like to deſtroy the ſame in thee.</p>
            <p>And as for the Devill carrying Chriſt up into the holy City, and ſetting him upon a pinacle of the Temple, and ſhewing him all the Kingdomes of the Earth in the twinkling of an eye, and ſaying, that thoſe Kingdoms were given to him; this holy City is thy ſelfe, O man, and thou haſt given it to the Devill, and he hath begot many wicked generations and kingdomes in thee which is his; and Chriſt taking thy ſinfull nature upon him to deſtroy it, the Devill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that nature of ſin thinks to exalt Jeſus, ſhewing him what kingdomes he had got in that nature, for which he would have him worſhip him, and hee would give him them all; but he reproves him and cares not for his wicked kingdomes, but crucifies him and them, and caſts him out of this nature, and makes this his humanity to worſhip God, and ſaith, Get thee from me Sathan, for I will worſhip my Lord and God; ſo Chriſt the divine power of God, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon him the ſinfull nature, had upon him the power of the Devill who thought to deſtroy him in it, ſo the Devill and hee being in one nature ſtrove for victory who ſhould have this nature for his poſſeſſion and dwelling place, the divinity hath the victory when the humanity conſenteth thereto, and then there is two againſt one, but if thou conſenteſt to the devill there is no fighting for thee, nor art thou worthy the fighting for; therefore if thou haſt a minde to ſtay with the Devill ſtill thou mayeſt, for hee will not pull thee out of his clawes againſt thy will: wherefore looke to it, O man, for there ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee life and death, chuſe life and live for ever; but if thou loveſt death, thou haſt death for ever.</p>
            <p>As concerning the Aſſe that Chriſt tooke away, and his curſing the fig-tree, it ſeemeth ſtrange in the letter, becauſe it contradicteth the truth, for the truth ſaith, that we ſhould uſe no violence, nor take any mans goods from him, and that we ſhould not curſe but bleſſe; but we ſee here that Chriſt hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Aſſe that was bound, and curſed the fig-tree againſt reaſon, for the time of figs was not yet come; therefore certainly there is another myſtery in it, for it cannot bee true according to the hiſtory that Chriſt ſhould doe ſuch
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111751:29"/>unjuſt things, for no falſhood nor guile was found in his hands: therefore this Aſſe is that ſimple innocencie that is tyed in thee with the cords of iniquity and cannot ſtir; for the humanity never did ride thereon, till Chriſt came in our humanity to make it free, and then he rideth into Jeruſalem the City of God meekly ſitting upon this Aſſe, which Aſſe is now the ſimple innocencie of God, on which (before Chriſt came into thy humanity) Balams did ride up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and did kicke and ſpurne this innocencie without a cauſe; therefore bee thou, O man, this ſimple innocent Aſſe, that the King of Sion may ride meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon thee to Jeruſalem the holy City of God.</p>
            <p>And for the fig-tree that had no time to bring forth its fruits but was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is the humanity that Chriſt did take upon him, induring therein the curſe of the law for the ſins cauſe, nor could it bring forth fruit till Chriſt came in it, and made it indure the curſe of the law, which made it ſeem to dye and vaniſh away: for this fig-tree or humanity, could not bring forth fruit till Chriſt came againe in ſpirit to vivifie and renue the ſame, for he is the life of the true fig-tree that bringeth forth fruit in due ſeaſon: ſo this firſt fig-tree that was accurſed ſhews unto us the firſt creation in man, how that it could not bring forth fruit being lyable to the curſe for ſins cauſe; and this tree is the humanity of Chriſt according to the fleſh, that indureth the judgement and curſe of God with us for firs cauſe, without cauſe in himſelfe, ſave only his love to us.</p>
            <p>And as for that certaine man that fell amongſt the theeves and was hurt, many paſſing by and would not helpe him till the Samaritane came: O man, this certaine man is thy ſelfe that is gone out of Ieruſalem (the City of God) to travell, and hath met with the Devill and all his company, which is pride, vaine-glory, hypocriſie, luſt, intemperance, wrath, envy, malice, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of ſpirit, covetcuſneſſe, evill cenſuring, murtherous mindes, and all the wickedneſſe that is: and theſe are the theeves that hath robbed thee of all goodneſſe, wounding thy ſoule, and leaving thee for dead: ſo the Prieſt and Levit that paſſeth by thee is the law, wrath, and curſe of God that is upon thee, and leaves thee alone to thy ſelfe for thy condemnation, becauſe thou baſt left the city and houſe of God to travell thou knoweſt not whither to loſe and damne thy ſelfe with the Devill and all his Angells and wicked ſpirits, that hath killed and ſpoyled thy ſoule, for thy wounds of ſinne ſtinke and are puttified within thee (as David ſaith, my wounds are feſtred and ſtinke within me) and ſo we lye as dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes till the good Samaritane (which is Ieſus Chriſt) come and have mercy on us, and take us up and ſet us upon his Aſſe which is his moſt innocent and harmleſſe life, whereon he carries thee as halfe dead, and after poureth in the oyle of his gracious goodneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy wounds to heale them, ſo that hee becommeth a plaiſter for thy ſores to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111751:29"/>heale thee, and indures all thy ſtinking filthineſſe upon him, for hee hath thy ſores in his ſalve which is himſelfe, and is that moſt innocent and harmleſſe life, and hee it is that beares the iniquities of us all, for all our ſinnes and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions is upon him; ſo this holy Chriſt is in hell in us till wee are cured of ſinne, for he is a ſalve for our ſtinking ſores that is a hell to him, and he indures thee, and the wrath of God upon thee, which is upon him in thee, till thou art perfectly cured and made whole from all blemiſh or ſpot: O how great is the love of God to thee, O man! why doth not thy heart melt in love to him againe, ſeeing he is ſo good to thee? Where, O man, canſt thou finde ſuch a love and lover, or ſuch goodneſſe as he is to thee without any cauſe of thine, but for his owne goodneſſe ſake whereby he takes pity on thee to helpe and ſave thee? therefore, O man, (whoſoever thou art that is dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes) if thou doſt not feele this power of God Jeſus Chriſt in thee, who is a ſalve for all ſores (which doth draw, ſcoure and waſh them within thee, and put thee to paine with the power of his working ſalves) thou ſhalt never bee well, thinke or believe what thou wilt of Chriſt without thee, and of his great works, he nor they ſhall profit thee nothing unleſſe thou haſt the power of Chriſt working within thee, and that thou ſenſibly feele the power of his working againſt ſinne in thee, which is a grievous hell and torment to thee for the preſent to indure; but thou hadſt better indure this hell againſt thy ſin for a moment, then be for ever loſt and damned, and be deprived of God and goodneſſe for ever, having the ſting of conſcience ſtinging thee for what thou haſt done, and for what thou haſt loſt and deprived thy ſelfe off for ever: therefore, O man, looke to it in time whilſt time doth laſt, for this world is time, the which if thou miſpendeſt there is no time more; and in this time is all worlds opened to thee, and if thou doſt not chuſe the divine and moſt holy world in this time, it is for ever ſhut up againſt thee, and ſo thou art deprived of God and goodneſſe, and art in a moſt miſerable condition: wherefore, O man, doe not dally with thy ſelfe, nor deferre the time, putting it off from one time to another; for time is a thiefe and ſteales away from thee, therefore do not cheat or coſen thy ſelfe with falſe beliefes and faiths of Ieſus Chriſt, and what he hath done for thee, the which he never hath done till thou feele the power of his working in thee with many agonies and bloody ſweats; and till thou feele the nailes of his crucifying pricke thee to the very heart, and that thou feeleſt the ſtings of death for ſinne in thee; therefore O man, put no confidence in Chriſt till thou findeſt the mighty power and worke of Chriſt in thee; for if thou doeſt thou deceiveſt thy ſelfe, and thy beliefe is in vaine, and a dead faith without this worke of Chriſt working mightily in thee, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe all thy ſtrong holds of ſinne and vaine imaginations, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111751:30"/>thee up a pure ſoule to his Father, that God may be all in all in thee: O that it were ſo come to paſſe in all ſoules, then were they happy, but till then moſt unhappy.</p>
            <p>And for that man that was ſaid to be borne blinde, is Chriſt after the fleſh in thee, which became thy ſelfe, who is conceived and borne in iniquity in thee to ſave thee; for thy father (which is the devill) is become his father and thy mother (which is luſt) is become his mother; and Ieſus Chriſt is that true Phyſitian that maketh himſelfe ſee in thee, and Chriſt ſaying to his Diſciples that the father of this blind man ſinned not, nor the ſon, is meant that as he is Chriſt (the holy unction or anointing) he commeth of God, and is the Sonne of God, and God is his Father, and they be no ſinners, neither he nor his Son; but Chriſt to ſhew the glory of God became this blinde man in us, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his owne eyes in us, which ſee not in man any good thing till ſinne is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed out of the man: ſo theſe holy eyes are blinde in us, till that time that Chriſt have deſtroyed ſinne out of us, and then he openeth his owne eyes in us, which eyes then are ours which ſinne had blinded in us before, ſo that we could not ſee with thoſe righteous eyes, but made thoſe eyes to us to bee the eyes of the wicked nature, through which we looked not as they were in deed and in truth (righteous and holy eyes) but as they ſeemed to us, in ſo much that we have taken the holy God to be that to us which he is not in himſelfe, for our ſinnes hath made us thinke him our enemy when as hee is our deareſt, friend, that till our ſinnes are deſtroyed he doth and will ſeeme ſo to us that which he is not in himſelfe, for his eyes ſhall be blinde to us, and his ears deaf to us, ſo that he will neither ſee nor heare when we call and cry to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a darke cloud of ſinne that ſeparateth him and us, and hee will not heare us till this cloud is taken out of the way, and that we become a true father and mother to him, for we have been wicked parents to him heretofore, and have brought him into all wickedneſſe and miſery, and have killed him in ſuffering for us as if he had done all wickedneſſe, when as there was no guile found in his mouth, but is that innocent Lambe that was ſlaine in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy world of ſin.</p>
            <p>Alſo thou art that woman that is bound with Sathan eighteen yeares, and art become double with his bonds untill thou goeſt to Chriſt, that he may looſe thee from the bonds of Sathan, and make thee whole and ſtreight again.</p>
            <p>And thou art ſhee that haſt that bloody iſſue of ſinne for twelve yeares: O touch therefore his garment, his fleſh or mortification, and thou ſhalt be made whole; and this garment is the law of ſinne which cleanſeth thee from ſinne.</p>
            <p>And thou art he that is poſſeſſed with legions of Devills or ſinnes; O then
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111751:30"/>let Chriſt by his mighty power caſt him out of thee that thou mayeſt be in thy right minde againe.</p>
            <p>And thou art the man poſſeſſed with a deafe and dumbe Devill, ſo that thou canſt not ſpeake to God, nor heare him when he ſpeaketh to thee: O faſt thou the true reall faſt, which is from all thy ſinnes) and pray to God continually, (with a broken and contrite heart and true ſorrowfull ſpirit) then mayeſt thou ſpeake to God and heare him when he ſpeaks to thee.</p>
            <p>And thou art or mayeſt be in that ſhip on that ſtormy ſea, that is ready to ſinck thy ſhip with its boiſterous waves, for God and the Devill are at ſtrife for thee, when thou haſt once joyned thy ſelfe to God, and then beginneth the bloody warrs betwixt theſe two Kingdomes in thee, for when thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed world of ſinne begins to be at an end, then is there Kingdom againſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and nation againſt nation in thee, and ſtormy rageing ſeas roaring, ſo that the heart of thy man of ſin begins to faile in thee, and Chriſt is aſleepe in the cabbin (that is in thy inmoſt ſelfe, and is that ſtill and ſoft voice) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeke for him and awake him that he may ſave thee, and calme theſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſtormy ſeas within thee, with his moſt ſtill and ſoft voyce: and theſe are the ſeas that St. Paul did ſaile through, God, and the Devill the truth, and thely, which claſheth one againſt the other, and the humanitie is the ſhip that ſaileth betwixt thoſe two ſeas and taſts of both and is broken, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of that ſhip that ſtuck faſt, (and was not hurt nor moved by the claſhing waves of thoſe ſeas) is the moſt holy and divine Godhead Jeſus Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee, which can indure, and is able to make thee indure (if thou ſtay in the ſhip with him) all the ſtormy ſeas of hell, death, and Devill. But the hinder part of the ſhip (which is the humanity,) muſt be broken becauſe of our ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, and muſt taſte of death for ſinnes cauſe, but nothing in the ſhip that ſtayes in it to indure this ſtorme of death ſhall periſh, and all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners that are bound in it ſhall be ſaved and ſwimme to ſhoare on the broken peeces of this ſhip: the true ſence and conſummation of all is, that when we have indured the battle till ſin be deſtroyed, then do we enter into the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life and are ſaved.</p>
            <p>Now to read the hiſtory of Chriſts laſt ſupper how that the ſame was kept in an upper Chamber, and that he did eat bread, and drinke wine, and give of the ſame unto his diſciples: and that he was whipt, ſcourged, and crowned with thornes, and how Judas ſold him, and how that he was afraid to die, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that hee did ſweate drops of blood, and that hee was nailed upon a Croſſe, and was pierced through with a Spearel, ſo that there came forth of his ſide blood and water, and that at his death the ſunne was darkened and the moone was put out, and that hee had gall and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111751:31"/>to drinke, and that he was crucified betweene two theeves. This is the moſt holy and ſacred myſtery which is acted in the ſoule of every man that is ſaved; and this upper chamber is thy inmoſt ſelfe, and this bread and wine, is the bitter cup of Gods wrath and indignation whereof thy ſoul muſt drinke for the ſinnes cauſe, and thou art not able of thy ſelfe to beare or drink this cup without ſome mighty power come to aſſiſt thee to doe it: now thy Judas or man of ſinne that is raiſed up to deſtruction, hath ſold the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent life into the hands of the wicked to ſuffer for thy ſinnes; for the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life commeth to thee in fearfulneſſe and trembling, and thou being in him (in this feare and trembling) prepareſt thy ſelfe to ſuffer with him; and thy Judas, Devill or wicked nature commeth to thee as if he were thy friend; and now ſeeing that thou wilt leave him hee fawneth on thee as if hee loved thee and were thy friend, ſaluting thee as if it were with a kiſſe of love; but he ſelleth thee to the blinde Jewes to be killed and crucified of them, which Jewes are thy blinde ſelfe will that now crucifies thy ſelfe and Saviour within thee, and thy ſelfe will carries thy ſelfe and Saviour into condemnation (with thy condemning conſcience) into the judgement hall of condemnation, where all thy ſinnes riſeth up againſt thee taunting, mocking and ſcourging thee, and crowning thee with the thornes of thy ſinfull life, which pricketh and woundeth thee and thy Saviour with griefe for what thou haſt done; ſo that thou and he art in a bitter agony and ſweat of death, inſomuch that thou deſireſt and wouldſt faine have this bitter cup to paſſe from thee; but thou muſt indure it if thou wilt be ſaved, for Gods will muſt be done and not thine, for it is he that raiſeth up all thy ſinnes againſt thee to condemne thee, crowning, whipping and ſcourging thee with what thou haſt done, ſo that thou muſt now taſte of the death of thy ſinnes or otherwiſe thou ſhalt never taſte of the life of God, for the life of thy ſinnes is the death of God in thee, and the life of God is the death to ſinne; and thou and thy ſinnes muſt be nailed to this croſſe, which croſſe is the patience and long ſuffering of Jeſus Chriſt in thee, unto which thou and thy ſinnes art nailed till thou art dead to thy ſinnes, and thy ſinnes to thee, for thy ſinnes hath nailed thee and thy Saviour together, and hath pricked him and thee to the very heart, ſo that he and thou doſt dye of thoſe wounds, and he and thou cryeſt out, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? and in the time of thy ſufferings (or Ieſus that makes thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this curſe or ſhamefull reproach of thy ſinnes according to thy due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert) the Son of glory, the life and brightneſſe of the Godhead is darkened or put out, ſo that there is all darkneſſe, death and hell over the internall divine, and moſt holy world, till thy ſinnes and thou art dead one unto another; ſo thou ſeeſt that the divine and moſt holy world is in hell under thy earthly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111751:31"/>till thy ſinnes be deſtroyed; and being in hell under thy body of ſinne and death, he raiſeth up all thy ſins againſt thee to condemne and ſhame thee, and ſhews thee what a partition wall is betwixt thee and him, which is the law of ſinne and death that condemneth thee, alwaies riſing againſt thee till ſinne be deſtroyed: ſo the love of God to thee offers thee his power, which is Ieſus Chriſt that enters into thee to deſtroy the body of ſinne in thee, which body of ſinne is the workes of the Devill that hath deſtroyed the body or works of God in thee. It is not the divine and holy God that is againſt thee, but it is thy ſinnes that ſtandeth in judgement againſt thee to condemne and arraigne thee, ſo that thou muſt goe under their judgement, condemnation and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for what thou haſt done againſt God and goodneſſe; for he it is not that is angry with thee, nor condemneth thee for he is that righteous and holy one that can indure all, and is one and the ſame for ever; nor can he be any other, for he cannot be moved to wrath or fury, for then were he changeable; but he is the unchangeable, and one and the ſame for ever; but the deeds that thou haſt done (againſt that holy One that is ſo good to thee) ſlyeth in thy face crying vengeance againſt thee, and telling thee that thou muſt dye for what thou haſt killed and caſt away from thee, ſo till the law of ſinne hath done his office and killed thee (for killing) and laid thee under the earth in hell (where thou haſt laid the holy One) thou ſhalt never be at reſt; for thou haſt killed, but art loath to be killed; but thou muſt caſt off this death or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou ſhalt be ignorant of juſtice, for juſtice is to reward every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his workes, and as he hath done to another, whether good or evill; ſo the moſt holy One by his mighty power inlightens thee, and ſhews thee all thy ſinnes how they ſlye in thy face againſt thee, and ſhews the juſtice of the law of ſinne, and that thou muſt dye for thy evill deeds, the which worketh feare and trembling in thy heart, and then doeſt thou cry and morne for helpe and can finde none, till the goodneſſe of God commeth to thee, taking pity and compaſſion on thee, and helpeth thee to indure the death of ſinne for ſinne in thee; ſo that now thou lyeſt on the patience of God till thou art freed from ſinne, and the Devill lyeth upon the other ſide of the patience or croſſe, and is that theefe that cannot repent, and thou art the other theefe that art repentant for what thou haſt done, and ſo findeſt mercy, and in that day or light of mercy thou ſhalt enter into Paradiſe thy Maſters joy, for now you have ſuffered together, you ſhall alſo riſe and relgne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and enter into the joy together, which joy lyes into thy inmoſt ſelf in the cave of thy earth, even there lyeth the moſt ſtill and ſoft voice, which was not in the great windes that did blow downe the rocks of ſinne, nor in that carthquake for ſinne, nor in that fire that conſumeth ſinne in which God is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111751:32"/>loſt to the man, for in that the man caſteth the holy God from him, is the very thing that doth condemne him and riſe againſt him, ſo that he can never be at reſt nor quiet till he hath found God againe; and even thus doth God appeare to the man that which he is not in himſelfe, even a conſuming fire, as he ſaith in Theſſalon. God ſendeth them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould believe lies becauſe they will not receive the love of the truth; for man thinketh that God is angry with him, and he neither can nor ſhall believe otherwiſe untill ſinne be deſtroyed out of him, for God doth ſeem to appeare in thy ſinnes as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry judge, condemning thee till thou haſt ſuffered under them and for them, and ſo worketh feare in thy heart, and all theſe angers that he ſeemeth to have againſt thee, and thoſe feares that he worketh in thy heart, is for thy future good, and for the great love he hath to thee recalling thee from thy ſinfull life, and when thou haſt forſaken ſinne, then he doth appeare to thee in his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, amiable and bright rayes full of ſweet raviſhing contents, and then thy Judas, Devill or ſinnes hath condemned themſelves in thee and with thee, and hath arraigned themſelves at the barre of Gods juſtice, and then they hang themſelves, in thee and breake their owne necks and bruſt their bowells a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, and ſo there is an end of them to thee, and an end of thee to them, and then thou cryeſt to thy Father or God. It is finiſhed, and ſo yeeldeſt up thy ghoſt or ſpirit into him, and the vaile (that is the fleſh of Chriſt that divided betwixt the holy and moſt holy place) is rent in twaine from the top to the bottome, which vaile, death or fleſh, is the long-ſufferance and patience of Chriſt, that raſteth in us till our ſinnes are extinguiſhed and blotted out, and this ſtandeth betwixt the holy place, and the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> and all that will be ſaved muſt taſte of this fleſh, death, patience, long-ſufferance, bitter cup, agony, or bloudy ſweat which ſtands before the holy of holies; and when wee have taſted this bitter death or cup, wee enter through this vaile, fleſh or death of Chriſt (which is the new and living way) into the holy of holies, or <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> which is the Kingdome of Heaven that is within you, and is peace, righteouſneſſe, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Now when the fleſh of Chriſt hath finiſhed his courſe, then is he taken out of the way, and then cometh hee againe to thee the ſecond time, and is thy holy Ghoſt or Spirit which leadeth thee into all truth, which truth is meekeneſſe, lowſineſſe of Spirit, gentleneſſe, lovingneſſe, rejoycing in mind, raviſhing thoughts, ſweet contemplations, ſinging Hymnes and Halelujahs, praiſe and thankſgiving to the Holy Ghoſt for their victoriouſneſſe, and this is thy ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing joy and comfort eternally, ſo that all the externall loſſes in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world doth not trouble thee, for thy mind is not below on theſe periſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things; for thou art dead to them and liveſt here as if thou livedſt not, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111751:32"/>uſeth all things here as if thou uſed them not, and if thou had all the honours and riches of this world thou wouldeſt diſpiſe them, and think them but dung and droſſe, for thou haſt farre more excellent honour and riches then this world can affoorde, but if by chance the Godly have the riches of this world, as it is but a chance, ſeeing the Godly and ungodly oftentimes injoy them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like here, he accounteth not the ſame his, but diſtributeth as he ſeeth need or neceſſity, as a faithfull ſteward, but the ungodly thinketh all that hee getteth here is his; and will ſuffer another to ſtarve and periſh by him, and in this thou may perceive a difference betwixt the Godly and ungodly, let them brag of their Chriſtianity as much as they will, their workes ſhow what they bee, but wee ſee what a Chriſtian is, and what a difficult thing it is to be one, and how many difficulties he muſt runne through, before he attain to the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Now to underſtand and read the hiſtory of the crucifying of Chriſt, of his condemnation, death, and buriall, what is this to thee or me, if we feele not the myſtery of his condemnation, death, and buriall, his reſurrection, aſcention, and comming to judgement in me and with me, for if we doe not ſuffer with him, we ſhall not reigne with him? therefore let us dye and bee buried with him, that we may ariſe and aſcend into the heaven with him, and from thence come to judge the quick and the dead, which dead is the ſinnes that is dead and loſt for ever out of us: and the quicke, is the living righteouſneſſe to raign in us for ever; therefore unleſſe I ſee the myſtery of theſe things wrought in me, the hiſtory thereof can do me no good, for in the hiſtory of the death of Chriſt, is ſhewed a great deale of weakeneſſe, for it is ſaid that hee was ſo mightily afraid of death, that he did ſweat drops of blood, and all the wrath of his Father did but extend to the death of the externall manhood upon the Croſse, but it ſeemeth ſtrange to me (that hee that had the power of heaven and earth) ſhould be ſo much afraid of an externall and bodily death, when there hath beene many ſince that have dyed for their religion, and for his ſake more terrible deaths: being drawn to peeces with wild horſes, fleyed, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alive, broyled, roaſted, boyled in lead, and all the terrible deaths that could be deviſed by wicked and devilliſh men to put them to, as is made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of in the booke of Martyrs, yet there was ſeene no ſuch weakneſſe in them, but they went to their deaths cheerfully, thinking themſelves happy to ſuffer for his ſake: Wherefore you may eaſily perceive, that there is a greater myſtery in the ſame which few doe ſee or diſcerne.</p>
            <p>For my part I do not deny the hiſtory of the Scripture, but doe beleeve that thoſe things were acted upon the Theater of this externall world, to ſhew to us what is acted upon the Theater of our internall world; but if we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111751:33"/>looke upon the hyſtory of Scripture, as things acted by other men, and take no more notice of it, we deceive our ſelves, for all the hyſtories points upon us, and we are the man intended; for when Nathan the Prophet came to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, he ſeemed to ſpeake to him of another, when as hee meant himſelfe, and David did conclude what the action repreſented to him in the perſon of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (by Nathan) was unjuſt, not thinking that the Prophet intended himſelf but another, and ſo judged him to death: but when the Prophet ſaid it was himſelf; and that he was the man; hee was ſorry, and loth to dye himſelfe, although he did judge the other to death, and thought he deſerved death juſtly: but in condemning the other he judged himſelfe. Therefore wee are the men that are to be condemned or ſaved, according as our deſervings are, and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is the reall truth, and is our true Nathan the Prophet that tells us what we have done, but he tells us our ſelves in hiſtories, and in the perſon of others, to try how farre we condemne others, and juſtifie our ſelves, but when wee condemne others we condemne our ſelves, for wee are the guiltie and that wicked man, therefore looke into the scripture as if it were thy owne ſoule, for all that is written there, is written in thy ſelfe: and there is the two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the table of ſtone, (thy ſtony heart) that is ingraven with a rough penne and with a thundering voice, which is the whole worke and curſe of the law for thy ſinnes, and the other table is the heart of fleſh, which is ſoft and mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the word that is written in thee, and is ready to obey all the words of the commandements that ſpeaketh in thee: but the table of ſtone (thy diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and ſtony heart) muſt be broken for thy ſinne and diſobedience cauſe, and for thy Idolatries and all thy ſinnes riſeing up againſt thee, crying venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſo that thy God (or goodneſſe in his great zeale) throweth downe thy ſtony heart, breaking it to peeces, and burneth up all thy Idoll Gods to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, makeing thee drinke up their aſhes (which is to make thee taſte of the death and loſſe of them) and ſtill his zeale is ſo great towards thee, that hee maketh thee ſheath thy ſword into thy brothers belly, which brother is thy neareſt ſelfe will or thy darling ſinnes, ſo when thou haſt fulfilled the will of thy Jelous God, he returneth to his place where hee was before, and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of ſtone or ſtony heart is turned to fleſh, and is obedient to the will of God and keepeth his commandements, the which I wiſh all Soules may do for their ſoules health and ſafety.</p>
            <p>There be many at this time that looke externally for an infallible ſpirit, when as the infallible ſpirit is internall in the ſoule of every man, for the ſame ſpirit is Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the word of life that is neare thee, even in thy heart and mouth to do it, and to be obedient unto the ſame; and he is that pearle hid in the field of thy heart, for which thou muſt ſell all that thou haſt to purchaſe this field that thou mayeſt injoy that pearle.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:111751:33"/>
            <p>And there are others that thinke that the externall body is the ſoule, and that it muſt dye and muſt anſwer for ſinne by that death, and that it muſt riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at the laſt day by Chriſt; therefore God cannot be their God whilſt their body is dead, for he is not the God of the dead but of the living; then whilſt they live here they may live as they liſt, and commit what ſinnes they will, for their body dying which they take for the ſoul) doth make ſatisfaction for their ſinne, which of neceſſity muſt draw this conſequence, that if one man kill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother he doth but the will of God, for he ſaith, the ſoul that ſinneth muſt dye: I wonder much what thoſe people (that hold ſuch opinions) can ſay or think of little children that dye in the wombe, or as ſoon as they are borne certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no man in reaſon can ſay that their ſoule hath ſinned, but you will alleadge their parents have ſinned for them, as others have ſaid; if it be ſo, the ſinne of one condemneth a great many that of themſelves hath not ſinned, the which to me appeareth to be altogether againſt reaſon and juſtice, and is againſt the nature of God to condemne the children for the ſinne of the parents, for Ezkiel ſaith 18. that this proverb ſhould be no more in iſrael, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had eaten four grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge; at he ſaith that every ſoule ſtandeth upon his owne bottome or its owne ſelfe, and the four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ſinneth ſhall dye: alſo there are many creatures or bodies (which they call ſoules) that are drowned in the ſea, and divers fiſhes have fed upon that body, or that which they call the ſoul, and theſe fiſhes have concocted or digeſted the ſoule of this man, and it is turned into the fleſh of a fiſh, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards this fiſh is taken, and another man or ſoule eats this fiſh which is the concocted ſoule of the other man, ſo that his ſoule is made fat and increaſed thereby, the one ſoule by eating the other, and Caniballs which are men, eat other men and are fed thereby: now when the ſoules of all theſe men are dead and concocted in thoſe that have eat them, how ſhall every one have his own proper ſoule at the laſt day when all the ſoules ſhall ariſe? I would willingly hear it proved by good reaſon how every one can have his owne ſoule againe, ſeeing they are all concocted and digeſted one in another: but perhaps you will ſay we muſt believe againſt reaſon, which is conſequently that we muſt believe an abſurdity; and the Apoſtle St. Paul deſireth to be delivered from unreaſonable men, which were abſurd and did believe againſt reaſon, for all men have not faith whoſe foundation is grounded upon reaſon; this body which they call the ſoule is dead without the ſpirit, as St. James witneſſeth in the ſecond Chap. where he ſaith, that as the body without the ſpirit is dead, even ſo is faith without workes; by which Scripture it is manifeſt, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without the ſoul or ſpirit is dead, and as is ſaid before, God cannot be their God, becauſe their body (which they tearm the ſoul is dead, ſo as he ceaſeth to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111751:34"/>be their God while they are dead, all which is contrary to ſenſe, reaſon and Scripture, where it is ſaid that he is the living God, and the God of the living and not of the dead; alſo it is contrary to ſenſe and reaſon in this, that that which is the God, good, felicity, or chiefe happineſſe of thoſe that live, and are rationall and ſenſible of the ſame, cannot in ſenſe, reaſon or Scripture, be ſaid to be the joy, happineſſe, or God of the dead, becauſe he is not ſenſible or capable of any joy, felicity or happineſſe at all.</p>
            <p>THe ſumme of all, and the whole diſcourſe of this Book is, that we ſhould feare to diſobey the holy God, but keep all his Commandements which is the whole duty of man, and to live a pure, exact, juſt and holy life, not doing to any man what we would not have done to us, but doing all the good to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that we would have done to us; and this is the infallible Spirit, Jeſus Chriſt, the power of God in us, which directs, corrects, inſtructs, perſwades, and makes us wiſe unto ſalvation; for he is the holy word of life unto us, and he is the Father, Elder, true Biſhop, and high Prieſt of our ſoules; ſo that we need no other Father, Elder, Biſhop, nor high Prieſt, but this holy Ieſus Chriſt in us, for he is the holy unction that we have from above, and the holy One that teacheth us all things, and diſcovers all myſteries unto us, leading us into all truth, if ſo be that we are obedient unto him; but if we are not obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto this infallible Spirit Ieſus Chriſt in us, then wee ſhall know nothing of God or of the Scripture, but it ſhall be a ſealed book, a dead letter, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming contradiction unto us: but I hope we ſhall all learne and bee taught of him, and declare every one to his friend and neighbour what the Lord (the infallible Spirit) hath done for his poore ſoule, ſaying, What we have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, heard, felt and taſted of the good word of life, that will we declare unto you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111751:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
